ISBN 978-1-349-95075-1      ISBN 978-1-349-95076-8    (eBook)

DOI 10.1057/978-1-349-95076-8

Library of Congress Control Number: 2016958910

© The Editor(s) (if applicable) and The Author(s) 2016
The author(s) has/have asserted their right(s) to be identified as the author(s) of this work in accordance with the Copyright, Designs and Patents Act 1988.
This work is subject to copyright. All rights are solely and exclusively licensed by the Publisher, whether the whole or part of the material is concerned, specifically the rights of translation, reprinting, reuse of illustrations, recitation, broadcasting, reproduction on microfilms or in any other physical way, and transmission or information storage and retrieval, electronic adaptation, computer software, or by similar or dissimilar methodology now known or hereafter developed.
The use of general descriptive names, registered names, trademarks, service marks, etc. in this publication does not imply, even in the absence of a specific statement, that such names are exempt from the relevant protective laws and regulations and therefore free for general use.
The publisher, the authors and the editors are safe to assume that the advice and information in this book are believed to be true and accurate at the date of publication. Neither the publisher nor the authors or the editors give a warranty, express or implied, with respect to the material contained herein or for any errors or omissions that may have been made.

Printed on acid-free paper

This Palgrave Macmillan imprint is published by Springer Nature
The registered company is Macmillan Publishers Ltd.
The registered company address is: The Campus, 4 Crinan Street, London, N1 9XW, United Kingdom

Acknowledgements

This project began to take shape when I was preparing the manuscript for my own volume, E. H. Carr: a Critical Appraisal, published by Palgrave in 2000. Therefore, I first need to thank all those who got me interested in Carr and those who then suggested that we reissue one of his great classics with an introduction and additional material that would not only help a new generation of students understand Carr more readily, but also explain how he came to write The Twenty Years’ Crisis in the first place, and why it exercised the influence it did – and still does. That great stalwart of the British intellectual scene, Bernard Crick, once admitted that of all the books he had ever read – and Bernard had read quite a few – it was Carr’s The Twenty Years’ Crisis that had possibly influenced him most. Many others would no doubt say the same thing, including Tim Farmiloe, who worked for Macmillan for many years. Though Tim was too young to publish The Twenty Years’ Crisis (that privilege was left to the future Prime Minister Harold Macmillan), he did work closely with Carr much later, and as a result encouraged me to get involved in my first venture into Carrdom. I would also like to thank Tim’s successor, Josie Dixon, as well as Alison Howson, who first suggested that we reissue the volume with flags flying and drum beating, and a painting by Lowry on the cover to set the whole thing off.

Robert Machesney, who is the keeper of the archives at the Macmillan HQ in Basingstoke, deserves special mention too, not only for the wonderful lunch he provided on my visit there, but for making available to me the Carr correspondence with his favourite publishing house. The letters are worth reading for all sorts of reasons, not the least of which are the light they throw on Carr’s determination as a successful author to negotiate such excellent terms! I would also like to express my gratitude to the librarians in the Special Collection in The University of Birmingham where the Carr Papers are housed, and which have been added to enormously since 2001 with such documents as the Carr diaries, as well as several previously unavailable letters. I would also like to thank Caroline Ellerby for working so efficiently and helping me get all the material ready for the book.

Moving closer to home, my sincerest gratitude must be extended to my good colleague Professor Ian Clark in the Department of International Politics at the University of Wales, Aberystwyth. As the proud owner of one of the few first editions of The Twenty Years’ Crisis it was Ian who made it possible for me to make a serious comparison of the original with the later editions of the book, thus hopefully clearing up once and for all any misunderstandings regarding some of the more controversial deletions Carr made when working on the book in the summer and autumn of 1945 before its appearance in 1946. Directly and indirectly, many other colleagues have helped too, but I would like to say a very special word of thanks to several in the ‘home of the discipline’ at ‘Aber’, including Ken Booth, the first holder of the E. H. Carr Chair in International Politics, Tim Dunne, who is more than just ‘the Boswell of the English school’, Richard Wynn Jones, who still has his doubts about Carr on the national question, Andrew Linklater, a worthy successor to Carr as Woodrow Wilson Professor, Brian Schmidt for raising important questions about the ‘first great debate’, Nick Wheeler for his sheer enthusiasm and who is at last getting the recognition he deserves, Mike Williams for sharing his insights about Morgenthau, Steve Smith for his continued friendship and support, and Colin Wight for his immaculate taste in critical realism and French reds. Gratitude must also be extended to Barry Buzan, Bob Cox, Robert Gilpin and Fred Halliday for supporting the book with their warm words of praise. Thanks as well go to Stefano Guzzini, Charles Jones and Peter Wilson for their many insights into Carr. I would also like to mention the three previous Chairs of the British International Studies Association – Chris Brown, Christopher Hill and Richard Little – for being so supportive during my term of editorship of the Association’s journal, the Review of International Studies, between 1998 and 2001. In many ways my work for the Review and my involvement with Carr seem to have been indistinguishable these last four years.

Finally, a very special mention for my wife Fiona and my four children, Annaliese, Ben, Dan and Nell, for always being there.

Michael Cox

Aberystwyth

Wales

June 2001

A Guide to the Secondary Literature on E. H. Carr

The appearance of The Twenty Years’ Crisis in late 1939 witnessed the start of a long and often acrimonious debate about the book – one that continues today and seems to show no sign of abating. The starting point for an understanding of how Carr was initially read and received has to be the two important essays by Peter Wilson, ‘The Myth of the First Great Debate’, in Tim Dunne, Michael Cox and Ken Booth (eds), The Eighty Years’ Crisis: International Relations 1919–1939 (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998), and ‘Carr and his Early Critics: Responses to The Twenty Years’ Crisis, 1939–1946’, in Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr: a Critical Appraisal (Basingstoke: Palgrave, 2000). Both books also contain much material on Carr himself. The various contributors in the former publication attempt to deploy some of Carr’s main categories to see whether or not they have much value for the study of the modern world system – and generally conclude that they do. The second study includes 15 essays that discuss the various facets of Carr’s contribution to intellectual life, with a number – those by Brian Porter, Tim Dunne, Andrew Linklater, Paul Rich, Randall Germain and Fred Halliday – dealing with Carr’s more specific contribution to international relations. The latter also contains the indispensable autobiographical note by Carr himself. Written only a couple of years before his own death in 1982, Carr explains 40 years after the first appearance of The Twenty Years’ Crisis that it was ‘not exactly a Marxist work’ but was nonetheless ‘strongly impregnated with Marxist ways of thinking, applied to international affairs’. He also confessed that he was a ‘bit ashamed’ of its ‘harsh realism’, and by way of compensation went on in 1940 and 1941 to write what he called ‘the highly utopian Conditions of Peace – a sort of liberal Utopia mixed with a little socialism but very little Marxism’. For essential background on how and why Carr came to write The Twenty Years’ Crisis (and a lot more besides), see Charles Jones’ somewhat oddly titled, but very useful study E. H. Carr and International Relations: a Duty to Lie (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998), which examines Carr’s ideas on world affairs between 1936 and 1946. Rather strangely titled too is the equally impressive biography of Carr written by Jonathan Haslam (a former student but not an acolyte of Carr), The Vices of Integrity: E. H. Carr, 1892–1982 (London: Verso, 1999). Two other works should also be consulted, more for what they have to say about the various ‘idealists’ whom Carr attacked than for Carr himself. They are David Long and Peter Wilson (eds), Thinkers of The Twenty Years’ Crisis: Inter-War Idealism Reassessed (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995) and Lucian Ashworth, Creating International Studies (London: Ashgate, 1998).

As Wilson shows, Carr’s study provoked something close to outrage among those whom he had either attacked directly or whose ideas he had disparaged. A number felt compelled to reply in kind to what they saw as a mischievous but potentially influential volume with little moral compass, and which came all too close, in their view, of suggesting that high ideas about peace, order and international law were little more than the ideologies of the powerful states seeking to defend the status quo against the ‘have-not states’ such as Nazi Germany. Significantly, one of the more significant contributions came from the noted liberal Norman Angell in his Why Freedom Matters (Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1940). Leonard Woolf also replied in his The War for Peace (London: Routledge, 1940) and ‘Utopia and Reality’, Political Quarterly, Vol. 11, No. 2, April–June 1940, as did Susan Stebbing in Ideals and Illusions (London: Watts and Co., 1941). His predecessor at Aberystwyth and first holder of the Woodrow Wilson Chair, Alfred Zimmern, also criticized Carr in ‘A Realist in Search of Utopia’, Spectator, 24 November 1939; so too did R. W. Seton-Watson in ‘Politics and Power’, Listener, 7 December 1939. See though the more positive reviews by two American writers, W. P. Maddox in American Political Science Review, Vol. 34, No. 3, 1940, pp. 587–8, and Crane Brinton, ‘Power and Morality in Foreign Policies’, Saturday Review, 17 February 1940. However, it was left to the British socialist Richard Crossman to make what many thought was the most damaging political point of all: that in his rush to demystify power in international relations, Carr ended up writing an apologia for the foreign policy of Germany in the late 1930s; see his ‘The Illusions of Power’, New Statesman, Vol. 28, No. 475, 25 November 1940, pp. 761–2. An anonymous reviewer of the book probably summed up the general view of The Twenty Years’ Crisis that it was as ‘profound’ as it was ‘provocative’ (Times Literary Supplement, 11 November 1939, p. 65).

In spite of, or perhaps even because of the various attacks on the book, it did remarkably well. The first edition of 1939 was reprinted three times in 1940, and a new (and controversially modified) edition came out in 1946. This in turn was reprinted on 12 occasions until 1978, before the reissue of the book in 1981. Carr thus had many good reasons – somewhere close to 50,000 in fact – to be pleased by a volume that not only sold well at home but also in the US. Indeed, Carr himself was well aware of the importance of the American market, and on at least two occasions in 1948 wrote to his publishers, Macmillan, urging them to keep the US market well stocked. This was in part because the book, he found out, was ‘now being fairly widely used as a textbook’, and also because of what he discovered at first hand to be the growth of a new discipline in American universities known as international relations! ‘The study of the subject is increasing by leaps and bounds’ and so ‘the chances of sales are good’, he noted. Hence, the ‘more’ copies of The Twenty Years’ Crisis that Macmillan could ‘supply America at present, the more are likely to be sold here’.

No doubt sales were much helped by an early assessment penned by one of the more senior figures in the new field of American international relations: Hans J. Morgenthau. Writing the first review article in the very first edition of the newly established journal World Politics, Morgenthau readily conceded the importance of the book and the sharp intellect of the man who had written it. Carr’s contribution to political thought, he agreed, was ‘of the first order’. Yet Carr in his view had failed to temper his own form of realism with a clear statement of moral purpose; consequently, he had become what Morgenthau called ‘a Machiavelli without virtu’, that is, someone who had no ‘transcendent point of view from which to survey the political scene and to appraise the phenomenon of power’; see Hans J. Morgenthau, ‘The Political Science of E. H. Carr’, World Politics, Vol. 1, No. 1, October 1948, pp. 127–34. The influential Morgenthau piece was later reprinted in a shortened form, and with a different, rather more pungent title – ‘The Surrender to the Immanence of Power: E. H. Carr’ – appearing in his edited collection Dilemmas of Politics (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1962), pp. 350–7. For a later criticism of Carr, which takes up the issue of power and morality (and a good deal more), it is also useful to look at the quite lengthy essay by the American conservative academic Whittle Johnson, ‘E. H. Carr’s Theory of International Relations: A Critique’, Journal of Politics, Vol. 29, 1967, pp. 861–84.

Carr, however, had more friends than he did enemies in the US, and one of the more enthusiastic was Kenneth Thompson, a prolific writer and editor, and a great admirer of the classical tradition of realism, the finest proponents of which in his view included Carr, Reinhold Niebuhr, Hans J. Morgenthau, Walter Lippmann and George F. Kennan. For a brief guide see in particular Kenneth Thompson, Political Realism and the Crisis of World Politics (New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 1960), and his edited collection Masters of International Thought: Major Twentieth Century Theorists and the World Crisis (Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1980). Carr’s other great American admirer was of course Robert Gilpin, whose name was to become closely associated with the theory of hegemonic stability in the 1970s. Significantly, Gilpin derived this highly influential notion from his reading of Carr’s The Twenty Years’ Crisis, and then adapted it to international political economy. As he later admitted:

My interest in the relationship between the structure of the international political system and the nature of the international economy was first aroused by my reading of E. H. Carr, The Twenty Years’ Crisis. In this classic study of the collapse of the open world economy at the outbreak of World War I and the subsequent inability of a weakened Great Britain to re-create a liberal international economy after the war, Carr demonstrated that a liberal world economy must rest on a dominant liberal power.

(Cited in Robert Gilpin, Global Political Economy: Understanding the International Economic Order (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2001), p. 100)

In this context see Robert Gilpin, War and Change in World Politics (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1981) and The Political Economy of International Relations (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1987).

Given his canonical status in the US as one of the high priests of classical realism, it is not surprising that a good deal was to be written about Carr’s contribution to international relations theory. Useful starting points are: William C. Olsen, ‘The Growth of the Discipline’, in Brian Porter (ed.), The Aberystwyth Papers, 1919–1969 (London: Oxford University Press, 1972), pp. 3–29; Roger Morgan, ‘E. H. Carr and the Study of International Relations’, in C. Abramsky (ed.), Essays in Honour of E. H. Carr (London: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 1974), pp. 171–82; and W. T. R. Fox, ‘E. H. Carr and Political Realism’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 11, 1985, pp. 1–16. Fox is one of the many to have commented negatively on what he thinks are the important differences between the 1939 and 1946 editions of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. The critical chapter in Michael Joseph Smith’s book, ‘E. H. Carr: Realism as Relativism’, in his Realist Thought from Weber to Kissinger (Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1986), pp. 68–98, should also be read. Smith was one of the few Americans to refer to what he saw as some of the Marxist-influenced aspects of Carr’s thought. However, for a more favourable analysis see J. D. B. Miller, ‘E. H. Carr: The Realist’s Realist’, The National Interest, No. 35, Fall 1991, pp. 65–71. The title tells its own story about Miller’s reading of Carr. R.G. Kauffman’s ‘E. H. Carr, Winston Churchill, Reinhold Niebuhr and Us’, Security Studies, Vol. 5, 1995, pp. 322–33 is also useful.

Ironically, while Carr was taken very seriously in the US, in the UK at least there never appeared to be the same level of engagement. No doubt his apparent indifference to the subject of international relations itself, and his known sympathy for the Russian revolution, made him something of a marginal figure in Cold War Britain. It was not insignificant, of course, that he was not invited to attend the first meeting establishing the British Committee for the Study of International Theory in 1960. Nor was it insignificant that one of the first really serious attempts to deal with The Twenty Years’ Crisis was by someone who did attend: Hedley Bull. Furthermore, in a powerful critique originally entitled ‘E. H. Carr and the Fifty Years’ Crisis’, but finally published in 1969 under the title ‘The Twenty Years’ Crisis Thirty Years On’ (International Journal, Vol. 24, 1969, pp. 626–38), Bull called upon students of international relations to go beyond Carr and explore the idea that Carr rejected – ‘the idea of international society itself’ – and to use it as the starting point for a ‘new analysis’ of international relations. In the light of later discussions about Carr’s intellectual relationship to the cause of the so-called ‘English School’, this review takes on added significance, as do the various criticisms directed at Carr’s inability ‘to keep the balance, the fruitful tension between power and morality’ by that other high priest of the ‘school’, Martin Wight, in his International Theory: the Three Traditions (Leicester: Leicester University Press, 1991), pp. x, 16–18 and 267. In the same book Wight called The Twenty Years’ Crisis ‘the reflection of a diseased situation in Britain in the 1930s’ (p. 267). The vexed issue of Carr’s relationship, if any, with the ‘English School’ and the concept of an ‘international society’ can be followed up in Tim Dunne’s important Inventing International Society: a History of the English School (London: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 1998). See the criticisms of Dunne’s attempts to associate Carr with the ‘school’, and disassociate Manning, by Tony Brems Knudsen, ‘Theory of Society or Society of Theorists? With Tim Dunne in the English School’, Cooperation and Conflict, Vol. 35, No. 2, 2000, pp. 193–203; Samuel M. Makinda, ‘International Society and Eclecticism in International Relations Theory’, ibid., pp. 205–16; and Hidemi Suganami, ‘A New Narrative, A New Subject? Tim Dunne on the “English School”’, ibid., pp. 217–26. See also Tim Dunne’s reply to critics in his ‘Watching the Wheels Go Round: Replying to the Replies’, Cooperation and Conflict, Vol. 36, No. 3, 2001, pp. 314–18.

Carr, it is true, never bothered to reply to either Bull or Wight. Nonetheless, we do know from his unpublished correspondence that he had a rather low opinion of the notion of an ‘international society’. As he remarked in a letter to Stanley Hoffman in 1977, ‘no international society exists, but an open club without substantive rules’. A few years earlier he had said much the same thing in an attack on C. A. W. Manning’s book, later published under the title of The Nature of International Society (1962; London: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 1975).

‘My fundamental criticism’ [of his thesis about the existence of an international society], Carr wrote to the publishers even before they had decided to bring the volume out, ‘is that the international game implied by it is in fact a creation of a small and influential group in the Western world during the past 400 years and there is no reason to suppose that it will survive the decline of these groups.

On Manning’s contribution to, and role in, international relations in Britain, see the sympathetic account provided by Hidemi Suganami, ‘C. A. W. Manning and the Study of International Politics’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 27, No. 1, January 2001, pp. 91–108.

If Carr remained largely uninterested in international relations in Britain, not all practitioners of international relations were to remain so indifferent to him. This expressed itself from the 1970s onwards, however, not in a reaffirmation of his realism, but in a discovery of what many now said had for too long been ignored or misunderstood – namely, his critical attitude to power and those who exercised it. The first to hint at the puzzling and progressive character of Carr’s realism was probably Graham Evans in his original but unfortunately largely ignored, ‘E. H. Carr and International Relations’, British Journal of International Studies (after 1980 The Review of International Studies), Vol. 1, No. 2, 1975, pp. 77–97. The critical and historical theme was then taken up by the radical political economist Robert Cox, a very early fan of Carr, in his influential manifesto-like article ‘Social Forces, States, and World Orders: beyond International Relations Theory’, Millennium, Vol. 10, No. 2, Summer 1981, pp. 126–55. Of equal significance was Ken Booth’s inaugural lecture delivered in Aberystwyth in 1991, ‘Security in Anarchy: Utopian Realism in Theory and Practice’, later published in a slightly modified form in International Affairs, Vol. 67, No. 3, 1991, pp. 527–45. Andrew Linklater also played an important part in drawing attention to the more critical side of Carr. Among other things see his Beyond Realism and Marxism: Critical Theory and International Relations (London: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 1990); ‘The Question of the Next Stage in International Relations Theory: A Critical-Theoretical Point of View’, Millennium, Vol. 21, 1992; and ‘The Transformation of Political Community: E. H. Carr, Critical Theory and International Relations’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 23, 1997, pp. 321–8. See also: Paul Howe, ‘The Utopian Realism of E. H. Carr’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 20, 1994, pp. 277–97; Richard Falk, ‘The Critical Realist Tradition and the Demystification of Inter-State Power: E. H. Carr, Hedley Bull, Robert Cox’, in Stephen Gill and James H. Mittelman, Innovation and Transformation in International Studies (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997); and Vendulka Kubalkova, ‘The Twenty Years’ Catharsis: E. H. Carr and IR’, in Vendulka Kubalkova, Nicholas Onuf and Paul Kowert (eds), International Relations in a Constructed World (Armonk: Myron Sharpe, 1998), pp. 25–57. For an interesting, but brief discussion of Carr by a Marxist, see Justin Rosenberg’s observations on Carr as one of many troubled realists in his The Empire of Civil Society (London: Verso, 1994), pp. 10–15.

Carr’s ideas clearly continue to excite interest. His views on nationalism, for example, are discussed by Ernest Gellner in ‘Nationalism reconsidered and E. H. Carr’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 18, 1992, pp. 285–93, a sympathetic but not uncritical analysis. For a constructivist reading of Carr see Cecilia Lynch, ‘E. H. Carr, International Relations Theory and the Societal Origins of International Legal Norms’, Millennium, Vol. 23, No. 3, 1994, pp. 589–620, who attacks Carr for too easily dismissing the applicability of law, ethics and international organisations for the regulation of relations between states. It is also important to consult the three essays by Charles Jones, ‘E. H. Carr through Cold War Lenses: Nationalism, Large States and the Shaping of Opinion’, in Andrea Bosco and Cornelia Navari (eds), Chatham House and British Foreign Policy 1919–1945: the Royal Institute of International Affairs During the Inter-War Period (London: Lothian Foundation, 1994), pp. 163–85; ‘E. H. Carr, Ambivalent Realist’, in Francis A. Beer and Robert Hariman (eds), Post-Realism: the Rhetorical Turn in International Relations (East Lansing: Michigan State University Press, 1996), pp. 95–119; and ‘Carr, Mannheim and a Post-Positivist Science in International Relations’, Political Studies, Vol. XLV, 1997, pp. 232–46 where Jones explores the relationship between Carr and modern post-positivism through a reading of Mannheim. A provocative analysis of Carr’s relationship to inter-war ‘idealism’ is also provided by the American scholar Brian C. Schmidt, The Political Discourse of Anarchy: a Disciplinary History of International Relations (New York: State University of New York Press, 1998). For a more general overview see Michael Cox, ‘Will the real E. H. Carr please stand up?’, International Affairs, Vol. 75, No. 3, July 1999, pp. 643–53. On realism – again – look at Randall L. Schweller and William C. Wohlforth, ‘Evaluating Realism in Response to the End of the Cold War’, Security Studies, Vol. 9, No. 3, Spring 2000, pp. 86–107 where the two Americans use Carr’s thesis about ‘peaceful change as an adjustment to the changed power relations’ as a way of explaining the end of the Cold War. Finally, Stefano Guzzini’s ‘The Different Worlds of Realism in International Relations’, Millennium, Vol. 30, No. 1, 2001, pp. 1–11, and Peter Wilson’s ‘Radicalism for a Conservative Purpose: The Peculiar Realism of E. H. Carr’, ibid., pp. 123–36, provide a much wider perspective on realism in general and Carr in particular.

From the First to the Second Editions of The Twenty Years’ Crisis: A Case of Self-censorship?

By the end of the Second World War, E. H. Carr had achieved something of a minor celebrity status. The first edition of The Twenty Years’ Crisis had been reviewed widely and within a few months of publication in late 1939 had been printed four times, with early sales somewhere close to 8,000. By 1945 the book had even been translated into Spanish and Swedish. In 1942 Carr had then brought out his more forward-looking and altogether more popular study The Conditions of Peace – a powerful analysis of the world crisis with a set of policy recommendations to follow. Indeed, Carr was so confident of the message it contained that he requested that his publishers send a copy to President Franklin Roosevelt at the White House;1 they in turn wondered whether or not he would be prepared to write a ‘sequel’, which was bound to be ‘very popular both here and in the America’.2 Carr declined. Finally, there were his regular leader columns in The Times of London, which by the end of the war had earned him the wrath of the Prime Minister, and the unofficial title of the ‘Red Professor of Printing House Square’ from those who neither liked his argument for economic planning, nor his ongoing advocacy of a post-war alliance between the Soviet Union, America and Britain. Carr may not have been a household name exactly, but he did have what one critic termed ‘a strong position with the public’.3 Certainly, it was strong enough to provoke an outburst by F. A. Hayek in his famous study The Road To Serfdom, published the following year. Carr, Hayek believed, was one of the ‘totalitarians in our midst’ whose ‘contempt’ for ‘all ideas of liberal economists’ was ‘as profound as that of any’ expressed by any German thinker in the past. In fact, according to Hayek, he was probably one of the more dangerous of that particular breed who were currently threatening the cause of political liberty and economic freedom in Britain; consequently his views had to be taken very seriously indeed by all those who wished to defend both.4

Ever keen to make the most out of their very prolific rising star (in 1945 Carr had just signed a contract to write a study of Soviet Russia, in the same year he had brought out Nationalism and After, 1946 saw the appearance of another edition of his hugely popular International Relations Between the Two World Wars, as well as his Soviet Impact on the Western World), it made perfect sense for Macmillan to publish a new edition of the already well known The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Carr was obviously enthusiastic too, and though not insensitive to the controversy the book had already created, was keen to see the volume back in the bookshops. On 23 July 1945, he thus returned the corrected galleys to Lovatt Dickson at Macmillan, and four months later, in November, sent back the corrected proofs with a new index made necessary by virtue of the fact that he had made some alterations to the original text of 1939.5 However, as he explained in the preface to the second edition, these were of no great import. He wrote ‘I have changed nothing of substance and have not sought to modify expressions of opinion merely on the grounds that I should not unreservedly endorse them today’. Yet he did concede that he had changed a few things. Nothing of significance perhaps. However, he had, to use his own words, ‘recast’ some ‘phrases which would be misleading or difficult to readers now far remote in time from the original context’, modified ‘a few sentences which have invited misunderstanding’, and removed ‘two or three passages relating to current controversies which have been eclipsed or put in a different perspective by the lapse oftime’.6

What were these modifications, and how substantial were they? Carr thought they were minor. Others since have disagreed, including the well known American academic William T. R. Fox, famous for many things, but especially for having coined the term ‘superpowers’ back in 1944. In the first E. H. Carr Memorial Lecture given in Aberystwyth in 1984, Fox argued that the deletions that Carr said were trivial were perhaps not trivial at all, but ‘crucial’. Fox admitted to being ‘shocked’ when he discovered what had been omitted from the original edition of 1939. For what he discovered, and what made him indignant ‘initially’, was a series of cuts pertaining to the Munich agreement of 1938 and Carr’s less than sensitive references to the fate of Czechoslovakia. Fox, to be fair, did understand why Carr had made the changes. After all, The Twenty Years’ Crisis, he reasoned, was a text of its time, which saw itself as an intervention into the policy debates of the late 1930s – on the side of appeasement – but which also contained what Carr hoped, and Fox agreed, were some fundamental statements about the nature of international relations. So deleting a few phrases here and there was perhaps no bad thing as this helped ‘shed’ the book’s ‘period piece aspect’ and allowed it to ‘stand on its more enduring merits’. The real issue in fact was not whether Carr should have made the changes in 1945 for the 1946 second edition, but whether he might have done so back in late 1939, just before the book was about to be published, but when it must have been perfectly obvious that appeasement as a policy was in tatters. However, as Fox went on to speculate, the reason Carr did not do so was possibly because he still hoped that the final plunge into total war could be avoided after the initial ‘phony’ skirmishes in late 1939. Thus there was no reason to delete the offending passages. By leaving them in he might even be able help avert the ‘pointless carnage’ that was bound to follow if his argument was either ignored by policy-makers or rendered irrelevant by Hitler’s bombers.7

Fox was neither the first nor was he to be the last to comment on Carr’s revisions. He also included a couple of the deleted passages by way of illustration. What he did not do – and in the context of a short article could not do – was to include all the deletions. Hence, while many students might be aware of the fact that certain changes were made, they are unable to judge how important these are, and whether or not they represent a major or minor modification to the original text of 1939. In the normal run of things this would not matter; except that in this particular case, the very existence of the alterations has led to suspicion regarding Carr and possibly even about the probity of the second edition of The Twenty Years’ Crisis itself.

To clear up the ‘mystery’ of the missing passages, it might be useful to begin with a brief discussion of Carr’s views on appeasement. As is well known, Carr had always felt that the inter-war system was deeply flawed, and that one of the reasons for this was Germany’s impossible position as a ‘have-not’ state within it. Change to this system was therefore inevitable, and it was better that this occurred through negotiation around an agreed agenda rather than by any other means. This of course is why Carr was preoccupied with the whole notion of ‘peaceful change’ (the title of the crucial Chapter 13), and why he had been researching the subject so assiduously since he had resigned from the Foreign Office in early 1936. Indeed, in the same year that he had taken up his new academic post in Aberystwyth in Wales, he had become closely involved in a discussion group at Chatham House in London, the very purpose of which was to explore the issue.8

Thereafter, as his diaries reveal, he read widely on the subject in preparation for the volume that was finally published three years later in the form of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. One could even argue that one of the many reasons why he wrote the book in the first place was to provide a theoretical, as opposed to a political explanation as to why peaceful change in the European system was a perfectly acceptable principle, and that there was no reason why it should not be applied to Germany as well. Germany after all had been dealt a very tough hand at Versailles. The whole structure of the inter-war system had then been rendered non-viable by what Carr, among others, regarded as the indiscriminate use of the slogan of self-determination in 1919 (this is why he was especially critical of the Americans in general and Woodrow Wilson in particular). Moreover, it seemed to Carr, as it did to nearly everybody else within the political class at the time, that Britain’s real interests in the world lay outside of Europe and not within it. Thus Britain had no serious reason for opposing Germany’s legitimate desire to change a status quo that Carr never believed was defensible anyway. All this, and much more, about the real-world situation, including some fairly negative statements regarding the rights of small nations and the importance of big ones, can be found running like red threads through the whole of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Furthermore, these can be found in both editions of the book, which in terms of overall argument and structure are virtually identical.9

The changes that Carr made, therefore, need to be put into perspective. In no way do they alter the book’s central claims. Nor do they do anything to modify his analysis of peaceful change in the international system. On the other hand, he does leave out some of the details and examples that he employed in the first edition; the reason, one must suspect, is because to those reading the volume in 1946 as opposed to 1939, they were bound to rankle somewhat. In fact, to be told that Munich was no bad thing after the searing experience of war and the failure of appeasement as a policy, might have annoyed a very large number of people indeed! Carr also made more than just one change to the original text, and while some of these were of no real importance at all, one or two were fairly blunt. Thus Carr decided to get rid of them, not to hide his opinions so much as to ensure that some of the more embarrassing sentences did not get in the way of the main thesis.

The bulk of the amendments are to be found in the chapter on peaceful change. Having discussed the issue in general terms, Carr then cites two examples of ‘peaceful change’ in action (in the first edition though not in the second).10 The less controversial of the two (which remained in the second edition) was the nineteenth-century case of Bulgaria, which in 1877 had been deprived of much of the territory it had originally gained as a result of the Treaty of San Stefano. Whether or not this was fair did not much concern Carr: what did was that this change was brought about not by a war between the major powers of the time, but following ‘discussions round a table in Berlin’. It was at this point that he made his first significant deletion by removing from the second edition a more modern example of another case where peaceful change had come about through negotiations around another table in Germany. He wrote in the first edition, but not in the second:

If the power relations of Europe in 1938 made it inevitable that Czecho-Slovakia should lose part of her territory, and eventually her independence, it was preferable (quite apart from any question of justice or injustice) that this should come about as the result of discussions round a table in Munich rather than as the result either of a war between the Great Powers or of a local war between Germany and Czecho-Slovakia.

Carr could not be more explicit. Part of Czechoslovakia was going to be taken by Germany anyway, given the balance of power in Europe in 1938. Far better that it happen through reasoned debate between the ‘great powers’ rather than war. Thus in defence of the proposition that peaceful change was bound to be better than war – this being the ultimate purpose of statecraft after all – Carr felt no qualms about justifying Munich. Four paragraphs on, he then made yet another alteration in the context of a much wider discussion of what he called in both editions ‘the failure to achieve a peaceful settlement with Germany in the period between the two world wars’. There was a broad consensus, he argued, that some parts of the settlement in 1919 had been ‘just’ and some ‘unjust’, and it was only a matter of time before the ‘unjust’ parts were rectified. ‘Unfortunately’ Germany did not have enough power in the 1920s to do anything to change the situation, and by the time it did, after Hitler assumed office, it addressed the problem in a rather different fashion. At this point Carr changed the wording somewhat, and in the second edition of 1946 he argued: ‘By the time Germany had regained her power, she had adopted a completely cynical attitude about the role of morality in international politics.’ In the original, first edition of 1939 he wrote:

By the time Germany regained her power she had become – not without reason – almost wholly disillusioned about the role of morality in international politics.

He then added:

There was not, even as late as 1936, any reasonable prospect of obtaining major modifications of the Versailles Peace Treaty by peaceful negotiation unsupported by the ultimatum or the fait accompli.

Here the main argument is not affected, but whereas in the new edition Carr merely describes Germany adopting a cynical attitude towards morality, in the first he almost appears to justify what Germany did. After all, her disillusionment with morality was, according to Carr in 1939 (but not in 1946), ‘not without reason’. Moreover, whereas he seemed keen in every other circumstance to make the case for peaceful change, here he comes rather close to doing the opposite: that is, of providing a historical rationale of Germany threatening to use force. Indeed, if she had not acted in a threatening manner, says Carr, ‘she’ (Germany) might not have achieved what he already thought the status quo powers ought to have conceded through peaceful negotiations anyway. The change in words might be subtle, but the change in meaning is less so.11

This brings us to the third modification. In both editions Carr is critical of the way in which the status quo powers dealt with Germany in the late 1930s. According to Carr, it was not wrong for them to have acquiesced in what Germany did in Europe before 1938. What was wrong was to do so under protest. This, he went on, ‘inevitably created the impression that the remonstrating Powers acquiesced merely because they were unable or unwilling to make the effort to resist’, not because they felt the changes were either ‘reasonable and just’. Therefore what might have become a cause of ‘reconciliation’ became a factor in the ‘further estrangement between Germany and the Versailles Powers’, and so ‘destroyed instead of increasing the limited stock of common feeling which had formerly existed’.

In the first edition, however, we also discover the following:

In March 1939, the Prime Minister admitted that in all the modifications of the Treaty down to and including the Munich Agreement, there was ‘something to be said for the necessity of a change in the existing situation’. If, in 1935 and 1936, this ‘something’ had been clearly and decisively said, to the exclusion of the scoldings and protests by the official spokesmen of the status quo Powers, it might not have been too late to bring further changes within the framework of peaceful negotiation [and this, Carr continued] was a tragedy—for which the sole responsibility cannot be laid at Germany’s door.

Here Carr is not saying anything he had not said elsewhere before. However, whereas in 1946 he says nothing about direct responsibility, he does so in 1939 – and not all of it, he argues, is Germany’s. Furthermore, by citing the Prime Minister in March 1939, Carr is also suggesting that whereas his predecessors had got things wrong (in another volume published at almost the same time as The Twenty Years’ Crisis, Carr characterized their policy as oscillating ‘between two opposite and incompatible extremes’),12 the current British leader – Neville Chamberlain – might have got it right, or at least was prepared to accept what others had not: that Germany had a case and that measured change in the European order was both necessary and right.13

Carr then added another whole paragraph that did not appear in 1946. I quote in full:

The negotiations which led up to the Munich Agreement of September 29, 1938, were the nearest approach in recent years to the settlement of a major international issue by a procedure of peaceful change. The element of power was present. The element of morality was also present in the form of the common recognition by the Powers, who effectively decided the issue, of a criterion applicable to the dispute: the principle of self-determination. The injustice of the incorporation in Czecho-Slovakia of three-and-a-quarter million protesting Germans had been attacked in the past by many British critics, including the Labour Party and Mr. Lloyd George. Nor had the promises made by M. Benes at the Peace Conference regarding their treatment been fully carried out. The change in itself was one that corresponded both to a change in the European equilibrium of forces and to accepted canons of international morality. Other aspects of it were, however, less reassuring. Herr Hitler himself seemed morbidly eager to emphasise the element of force and to minimise that of peaceful negotiation – a trait psychologically understandable as a product of the methods employed by the Allies at Versailles, but nonetheless inimical to the establishment of a procedure of peaceful change. The principle of self-determination, once accepted, was applied with a ruthlessness that left to Germany the benefit of every doubt and paid a minimum of attention to every Czecho-Slovak susceptibility. There was a complete lack of any German readiness to make the smallest sacrifice for the sake of conciliation. The agreement was violently attacked by a section of British opinion. Recriminations ensued on the German side; and very soon any prospect that the Munich settlement might inaugurate a happier period of international relations in which peaceful change by negotiation would become an effective factor seemed to have disappeared.

Here at least Carr makes some attempt to scold Hitler for having acted without due regard to Czechoslovak sensibilities after he had invaded part of the country in 1938. Indeed, he blames Hitler for not having used the opportunity presented by Munich to build a new, improved relationship with the other great powers. However, Hitler’s actions are partly justified on the ‘understandable’ grounds that the Allies themselves had employed dubious methods at Versailles. Moreover, there was nothing wrong with what Germany then did in 1938. In fact, according to Carr, it was an almost textbook example of peaceful change. He even suggests that Czechoslovakia may have been partly to blame for what happened by not having treated well its own German minorities before Hitler decided to move in. He then adds some minor insult to injury by seeking to justify Munich in terms of a principle with which he had always had some fundamental problems – namely, self-determination. Ironic indeed if you happened to be Carr. Less ironic than tragic if you happened to be a Czechoslovakian.14

This leads us, finally, to discuss something that Carr did not change at all, though he clearly wanted to – and perhaps should have done. As he pointed out in the preface to the second edition of 1946, his ideas about the role and position of the nation-state in the international order had undergone considerable modification since the beginning of the war and the original appearance of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. While Carr conceded in the first edition that the ‘concept of sovereignty’ was ‘likely’ to ‘become more blurred’ in the future,15 he still accepted that the nation-state in some form or another would probably remain the basic unit of the international system. As he put it in 1939, ‘the nation is now, more than ever before, the supreme unit round which centre human demands for equality and human ambitions for predominance’.16 The final collapse of the inter-war system, the experience of war, and his belief by 1945 in the need for a totally restructured international economy, inclined him to a more radical conclusion: that the nation-state, both small and large, ‘was obsolete or obsolescent and that no workable international organization’ could ‘be built on a membership of a multiplicity of nation-states’. However, as he explained, he decided not to incorporate this shift into the new edition, and instead advised readers to look at his more recent book on the subject, Nationalism and After, published in 1945. Here they would be able to explore his ‘present views’ rather than those he had once held.17

It is of some interest, of course, that those who have been rather keen to point to those few passages where Carr provides an effective apologia for Munich, have said nothing about his equally important decision not to alter the text in a direction that might have better reflected his views on the nation-state. On the other hand, Carr himself made no reference to at least two alterations he did in fact make, one less significant than the other.

The first can be found in the final chapter where Carr questioned whether or not the nation-state would survive as the unit of power. Following a lengthy discourse about the rise of the nation-state in history and its possible transcendence – ‘few things are permanent in history and it would be rash to assume that the territorial unit is one of them’ – he went on to discuss those factors that were undermining the nation-state and leading to ‘the formation of ever larger political and economic units’. This tendency, he noted, ‘appears to have been closely connected with the growth of large-scale capitalism and industrialism, as well as with the improvement of means of communication and of the technical instruments of power’. He then made a brief qualifying statement in 1939 (but not in 1946) about the complex character of nationalism within the larger context of the trend towards ever larger units whose

course was marked by a conflict between the two functions of nationalism – the integrating and the disintegrating function. Prior to the middle of the nineteenth century, nationalism had been in the main a disintegrating force, breaking off fragment after fragment from the theoretical unit of mediaeval Christendom and making them into independent national units. Then nationalism, almost suddenly, passed over to an integrating role in Germany and Italy, and developed, in the most powerful countries, into an imperialism which seemed likely to divide the world into half dozen units of power.18

Why Carr should have dropped this is something of a mystery, unless he felt it was being a little too positive about nationalism as a factor in the making of the modern world. It is difficult to know, but does at least reveal the tensions in his own thought about the phenomenon. He then added (in both editions) that: ‘The War threw this development into conspicuous relief’.

The second change came a couple of pages later in the same discussion. At this point Carr shifted the discussion away from an analysis of those various pressures that were leading to the ‘concentration of political and economic power’. ‘That is’ only ‘one side of the picture’, he noted in the first edition of 1939; we also have to look, he said, ‘in the other direction’ where ‘disintegrating forces may still be found at work’. He continued:

It is a moot point whether the British Empire and the British Commonwealth of Nations are at present tending towards a strengthening or a relaxation of the bonds between the component parts. The United States are striving to extend their economic power by breaking down foreign tariff barriers. But simultaneously, within the Union, new trade barriers – still insignificant, but ever increasing – are being surreptitiously raised between the states themselves. It is not certain that Germany will be able to constitute Central and South-Eastern Europe, or Japan Eastern Asia, into a compact economic unit, or that Soviet Russia will be able to knit together her vast territories as industrial development progresses.19

One of the main reasons why Carr may have decided to remove this passage was because in the intervening years between the publication of The Twenty Years’ Crisis in 1939 and the new edition of 1946, certain changes had taken place: for example, Soviet Russia had been able to ‘knit’ its territories together, and the US after the war had not only begun to break down those external tariff barriers but had become more united itself. But it is also possible that he was keen to get rid of these few sentences here for another reason, for although they did not constitute a defence of the new empires then being created by Germany or Japan, nor were they especially critical. Admittedly, Carr did go on to suggest that they (and other imperial conglomerations) might not last because there ‘may be a size which cannot be exceeded without a recrudescence of the disintegrating tendencies’.20 However, this was not something that Carr seemed to look forward to with any enthusiasm. If anything, the logic of his argument led him to another, very different conclusion: that big units were good and small ones were bad – even if the units in question happened to be dominated by Nazi Germany and Imperial Japan. To have said as much in 1939 was problematic enough: to have repeated it in 1946 after the terrible price paid to eliminate both powers might have raised more than just a few eyebrows.

1.

|   |

E. H. Carr to Macmillan Publishers, 16 March 1942, Macmillan Publishers Archives (hereafter MPA).

2.

|   |

Macmillan Publishers to E. H. Carr, 16 August and 23 August 1943 (MPA).

3.

|   |

Gilbert Murray to Lord David Davies, 31 May 1943. University of Wales Aberystwyth Archives.

4.

|   |

F. A. Hayek, The Road to Serfdom (London: George Routledge and Sons, 1944), pp. 138–41.

5.

|   |

E. H. Carr to Macmillan Publishers, 23 July and 19 November 1945 (MPA).

6.

|   |

See ‘Preface to the Second Edition’, 15 November 1945, in this volume.

7.

|   |

W. T. R. Fox, ‘E. H. Carr and political realism: vision and revision’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 11, 1985, pp. 1–16.

8.

|   |

‘Discussion at Chatham House of Manning’s views on peaceful change’, 19 May 1936. Entry into the Carr Diaries, The University of Birmingham. The book that finally emerged from these discussions was edited by C. A. W. Manning under the title of Peaceful Change and was cited extensively by Carr in The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Manning at the time was Montagu Burton Professor of International Relations at the London School of Economics. Carr later thanked Manning for reading and commenting on The Twenty Years’ Crisis.

9.

|   |

One interesting little change that Carr did make was to change the designation of Hitler from ‘Herr Hitler’ in the 1939 edition to just ‘Hitler’ in the 1946 edition.

10.

|   |

Compare pp. 278 (first edition, 1939), 219 (second edition, 1946) and 199 (2001 edition).

11.

|   |

Compare pp. 281(first edition), 221 (second edition) and 201 (2001 edition).

12.

|   |

See E. H. Carr, Britain: a Study of Foreign Policy from the Versailles Treaty to the Outbreak of War (London: Longmans, Green and Co., 1939), p. 157. In the same volume Carr noted: ‘Mr Chamberlain perceived more clearly than any other political leader the growing danger of a policy of words not matched either by willingness or a capacity to act’ (p. 166)

13.

|   |

Compare pp. 281–2 (first edition), 222 (second edition) and 201 (2001 edition).

14.

|   |

Compare pp. 282–3 (first edition), 222 (second edition) and 201 (2001 edition).

15.

|   |

Cited in first edition on pp. 295–6; second edition, p. 230; 2001 edition, p. 212.

16.

|   |

First edition 1939, p. 291. In the second edition the ‘now’ was dropped. Carr thus wrote in 1946: ‘The nation became, more than ever before, the supreme unit round which centre human demands for equality and human demands for predominance’ (p. 227). 2001 edition, p. 210.

17.

|   |

See the ‘Preface to the Second Edition’, p. viii.

18.

|   |

See pp. 293–4 (first edition), 229 (second edition), 211 (2001 edition).

19.

|   |

See pp. 295 (first edition), 230 (second edition), 212 (2001 edition).

20.

|   |

First edition, p. 295; second edition, p. 230; 2001 edition, p. 212.

CHAPTER TWO

Utopia and Reality

The antithesis of utopia and reality – a balance always swinging towards and away from equilibrium and never completely attaining it – is a fundamental antithesis revealing itself in many forms of thought. The two methods of approach – the inclination to ignore what was and what is in contemplation of what should be, and the inclination to deduce what should be from what was and what is – determine opposite attitudes towards every political problem. ‘It is the eternal dispute’, as Albert Sorel puts it, ‘between those who imagine the world to suit their policy, and those who arrange their policy to suit the realities of the world.’1 It may be suggestive to elaborate this antithesis before proceeding to an examination of the current crisis of international politics.

Free will and determination

The antithesis of utopia and reality can in some aspects be identified with the antithesis of Free Will and Determinism. The utopian is necessarily voluntarist: he believes in the possibility of more or less radically rejecting reality, and substituting his utopia for it by an act of will. The realist analyses a predetermined course of development which he is powerless to change. For the realist, philosophy, in the famous words of Hegel’s preface to his Philosophy of Right, always ‘comes too late’ to change the world. By means of philosophy, the old order ‘cannot be rejuvenated, but only known’. The utopian, fixing his eyes on the future, thinks in terms of creative spontaneity: the realist, rooted in the past, in terms of causality. All healthy human action, and therefore all healthy thought, must establish a balance between utopia and reality, between free will and determinism. The complete realist, unconditionally accepting the causal sequence of events, deprives himself of the possibility of changing reality. The complete utopian, by rejecting the causal sequence, deprives himself of the possibility of understanding either the reality which he is seeking to change or the processes by which it can be changed. The characteristic vice of the utopian is naïvety; of the realist, sterility.2

Theory and practice

The antithesis of utopia and reality also coincides with the antithesis of theory and practice. The utopian makes political theory a norm to which political practice ought to conform. The realist regards political theory as a sort of codification of political practice. The relationship of theory and practice has come to be recognized in recent years as one of the central problems of political thought. Both the utopian and the realist distort this relationship. The utopian, purporting to recognize the interdependence of purpose and fact, treats purpose as if it were the only relevant fact, and constantly couches optative propositions in the indicative mood. The American Declaration of Independence maintains that ‘all men are created equal’, Mr Litvinov that ‘peace is indivisible’,3 and Sir Norman Angell that ‘the biological division of mankind into independent warring states’ is a ‘scientific ineptitude’.4 Yet it is a matter of common observation that all men are not born equal even in the United States, and that the Soviet Union can remain at peace while its neighbours are at war; and we should probably think little of a zoologist who described a man-eating tiger as a ‘scientific ineptitude’. These propositions are items in a political programme disguised as statements of fact;5 and the utopian inhabits a dream-world of such ‘facts’, remote from the world of reality where quite contrary facts may be observed. The realist has no difficulty in perceiving that these utopian propositions are not facts but aspirations, and belong to the optative not to the indicative mood; and he goes on to show that, considered as aspirations, they are not a priori propositions, but are rooted in the world of reality in a way which the utopian altogether fails to understand. Thus for the realist, the equality of man is the ideology of the underprivileged seeking to raise themselves to the level of the privileged; the indivisibility of peace the ideology of states which, being particularly exposed to attack, are eager to establish the principle that an attack on them is a matter of concern to other states more fortunately situated;6 the ineptitude of sovereign states the ideology of predominant Powers which find the sovereignty of other states a barrier to the enjoyment of their own predominant position. This exposure of the hidden foundations of utopian theory is a necessary preliminary to any serious political science. But the realist, in denying any a priori quality to political theories, and in proving them to be rooted in practice, falls easily into a determinism which argues that theory, being nothing more than a rationalization of conditioned and predetermined purpose, is a pure excrescence and impotent to alter the course of events. While therefore the utopian treats purpose as the sole ultimate fact, the realist runs the risk of treating purpose merely as the mechanical product of other facts. If we recognize that this mechanization of human will and human aspiration is untenable and intolerable, then we must recognize that theory, as it develops out of practice and develops into practice, plays its own transforming role in the process. The political process does not consist, as the realist believes, purely in a succession of phenomena governed by mechanical laws of causation; nor does it consist, as the utopian believes, purely in the application to practice of certain theoretical truths evolved out of their inner consciousness by wise and far-seeing people. Political science must be based on a recognition of the interdependence of theory and practice, which can be attained only through a combination of utopia and reality.

The intellectual and the bureaucrat

A concrete expression of the antithesis of theory and practice in politics is the opposition between the ‘intellectual’ and the ‘bureaucrat’,7 the former trained to think mainly on a priori lines, the latter empirically. It is in the nature of things that the intellectual should find himself in the camp which seeks to make practice conform to theory; for intellectuals are particularly reluctant to recognize their thought as conditioned by forces external to themselves, and like to think of themselves as leaders whose theories provide the motive force for so-called men of action. Moreover, the whole intellectual outlook of the last two hundred years has been strongly coloured by the mathematical and natural sciences. To establish a general principle, and to test the particular in the light of that principle, has been assumed by most intellectuals to be the necessary foundation and starting-point of any science. In this respect, utopianism with its insistence on general principles may be said to represent the characteristic intellectual approach to politics. Woodrow Wilson, the most perfect modern example of the intellectual in politics, ‘excelled in the exposition of fundamentals. His political method . . . was to base his appeal upon broad and simple principles, avoiding commitment upon specific measures.’8 Some supposedly general principle, such as ‘national self-determination’, ‘free trade’ or ‘collective security’ (all of which will be easily recognized by the realist as concrete expressions of particular conditions and interests), is taken as an absolute standard, and policies are adjudged good or bad by the extent to which they conform to, or diverge from, it. In modern times, intellectuals have been the leaders of every utopian movement; and the services which utopianism has rendered to political progress must be credited in large part to them. But the characteristic weakness of utopianism is also the characteristic weakness of the political intellectuals – failure to understand existing reality and the way in which their own standards are rooted in it. ‘They could give to their political aspirations’, wrote Meinecke of the role of intellectuals in German politics, ‘a spirit of purity and independence, of philosophical idealism and of elevation above the concrete play of interests . . . but through their defective feeling for the realistic interests of actual state life they quickly descended from the sublime to the extravagant and eccentric.’9

It has often been argued that the intellectuals are less directly conditioned in their thinking than those groups whose coherence depends on a common economic interest, and that they therefore occupy a vantage point au-dessus de la mêlée. As early as 1905, Lenin attacked ‘the old-fashioned view of the intelligentsia as capable . . . of standing outside class’.10 More recently, this view has been resuscitated by Dr Mannheim, who argues that the intelligentsia, being ‘relatively classless’ and ‘socially unattached’, ‘subsumes in itself all those interests with which social life is permeated’, and can therefore attain a higher measure of impartiality and objectivity.11 In a certain limited sense, this is true. But any advantage derived from it would seem to be nullified by a corresponding disability, i.e. detachment from the masses whose attitude is the determining factor in political life. Even where the illusion of their leadership was strongest, modern intellectuals have often found themselves in the position of officers whose troops were ready enough to follow them in quiet times, but could be relied on to desert in any serious engagement. In Germany and many smaller European countries, the democratic constitutions of 1919 were the work of devoted intellectuals, and achieved a high degree of theoretical perfection. But when a crisis occurred, they broke down almost everywhere through failure to win the durable allegiance of the mass of the population. In the United States, the intellectuals played a preponderant part in creating the League of Nations, and most of them remained avowed supporters of it. Yet the mass of the American people, having appeared to follow their lead, rejected it when the critical moment arrived. In Great Britain, the intellectuals secured, by a devoted and energetic propaganda, overwhelming paper support for the League of Nations. But when the Covenant appeared to require action which might have entailed practical consequences for the mass of the people, successive governments preferred inaction; and the protests of the intellectuals caused no perceptible reaction in the country.

The bureaucratic approach to politics is, on the other hand, fundamentally empirical. The bureaucrat purports to handle each particular problem ‘on its merits’, to eschew the formulation of principles and to be guided on the right course by some intuitive process born of long experience and not of conscious reasoning. ‘There are no general cases,’ said a French official, acting as French Delegate at an Assembly of the League of Nations; ‘there are only specific cases.’12 In his dislike of theory, the bureaucrat resembles the man of action. ‘On s’engage, puis on voit’ is a motto attributed to more than one famous general. The excellence of the British civil service is partly due to the ease with which the bureaucratic mentality accommodates itself to the empirical tradition of British politics. The perfect civil servant conforms closely to the popular picture of the English politician as a man who recoils from written constitutions and solemn covenants, and lets himself be guided by precedent, by instinct, by feel for the right thing. This empiricism is itself, no doubt, conditioned by a specific point of view, and reflects the conservative habit of English political life. The bureaucrat, perhaps more explicitly than any other class of the community, is bound up with the existing order, the maintenance of tradition, and the acceptance of precedent as the ‘safe’ criterion of action. Hence bureaucracy easily degenerates into the rigid and empty formalism of the mandarin, and claims an esoteric understanding of appropriate procedures which is not accessible even to the most intelligent outsider. ‘Expérience vaut mieux que science’ is the typical bureaucratic motto. ‘Attainments in learning and science’, wrote Bryce, voicing a widely felt prejudice, ‘do little to make men wise in politics.’13 When a bureaucrat wishes to damn a proposal, he calls it ‘academic’. Practice, not theory, bureaucratic training, not intellectual brilliance, is the school of political wisdom. The bureaucrat tends to make politics an end in themselves. It is worth remarking that both Machiavelli and Bacon were bureaucrats.

This fundamental antithesis between intellectual and bureaucratic modes of thought, always and everywhere latent, has appeared in the last half century in a quarter where it would hardly have been looked for: in the labour movement. Writing in the 1870s, Engels congratulated the German workers on the fact that they ‘belong to the most theoretical nation in the world, and have retained that theoretical sense which has been almost completely lost by the so-called “educated” classes in Germany’. He contrasted this happy state with ‘the indifference to all theory which is one of the chief reasons of the slow progress of the English workers’ movement’.14 Forty years later, another German writer confirmed this observation.15 The theoretical analysis of Marxist doctrine became one of the principal preoccupations of leading German Social Democrats; and many observers believe that this one-sided intellectual development was an important factor in the ultimate collapse of the party. The British labour movement, until the last few years, entirely eschewed theory. At present, imperfect harmony between the intellectual and trade union wings is a notorious source of embarrassment to the Labour Party. The trade unionist tends to regard the intellectual as a utopian theorist lacking experience in the practical problems of the movement. The intellectual condemns the trade union leader as a bureaucrat. The recurrent conflicts between factions within the Bolshevik party in Soviet Russia were in part, at any rate, explicable as conflicts between the ‘party intelligentsia’, represented by Bukharin, Kamenev, Radek and Trotsky, and the ‘party machine’ represented by Lenin, Sverdlov (till his death in 1919) and Stalin.16

The opposition between intellectual and bureaucrat was particularly prominent in Great Britain during the twenty years between the wars in the field of foreign affairs. During the first world war, the Union of Democratic Control, an organization of utopian intellectuals, strove to popularize the view that the war was largely due to the control of foreign affairs in all countries by professional diplomats. Woodrow Wilson believed that peace would be secured if international issues were settled ‘not by diplomats or politicians each eager to serve his own interests, but by dispassionate scientists – geographers, ethnologists, economists – who had made studies of the problems involved’.17 Bureaucrats, and especially diplomats, were long regarded with suspicion in League of Nations circles; and it was considered that the League would contribute greatly to the solution of international problems by taking them out of the reactionary hands of foreign offices. Wilson, in introducing the draft Covenant to the plenary session of the Peace Conference, spoke of ‘the feeling that, if the deliberating body of the League of Nations was merely to be a body of officials representing the various governments, the peoples of the world would not be sure that some of the mistakes which preoccupied officials had admittedly made might not be repeated’.18 Later, in the House of Commons, Lord Cecil was more scathing:

I am afraid I came to the conclusion at the Peace Conference, from my own experience, that the Prussians were not exclusively confined to Germany. There is also the whole tendency and tradition of the official classes . . . You cannot avoid the conclusion that there is a tendency among them to think that whatever is is right.19

At the Second Assembly, Lord Cecil invoked the support of ‘public opinion’, which the League was supposed to represent, against the ‘official classes’;20 and such appeals were frequently heard during the next ten years. The bureaucrat for his part equally mistrusted the missionary zeal of enthusiastic intellectuals for collective security, world order and general disarmament – schemes which seemed to him the product of pure theory divorced from practical experience. The disarmament issue well illustrated this divergence of view. For the intellectual, the general principle was simple and straightforward; the alleged difficulties of applying it were due to obstruction by the ‘experts’.21 For the expert, the general principle was meaningless and utopian; whether armaments could be reduced, and if so which, was a ‘practical’ question to be decided in each case ‘on its merits’.

Left and right

The antithesis of utopia and reality, and of theory and practice, further reproduces itself in the antithesis of radical and conservative, of Left and Right, though it would be rash to assume that parties carrying these labels always represent these underlying tendencies. The radical is necessarily utopian, and the conservative realist. The intellectual, the man of theory, will gravitate towards the Left just as naturally as the bureaucrat, the man of practice, will gravitate towards the Right. Hence the Right is weak in theory, and suffers through its inaccessibility to ideas. The characteristic weakness of the Left is failure to translate its theory into practice – a failure for which it is apt to blame the bureaucrats, but which is inherent in its utopian character. ‘The Left has reason (Vernunft), the Right has wisdom (Verstand),’ wrote the Nazi philosopher, Moeller van den Bruck.22 From the days of Burke onwards, English conservatives have always strongly denied the possibility of deducing political practice by a logical process from political theory. ‘To follow the syllogism alone is a short cut to the bottomless pit,’ says Lord Baldwin23 – a phrase which may suggest that he practices as well as preaches abstention from rigorously logical modes of thought. Mr Churchill refuses to believe that ‘extravagant logic in doctrine’ appeals to the British elector.24 A particularly clear definition of different attitudes towards foreign policy comes from a speech made in the House of Commons by Neville Chamberlain in answer to a Labour critic:

What does the hon. Member mean by foreign policy? You can lay down sound and general propositions. You can say that your foreign policy is to maintain peace; you can say that it is to protect British interests, you can say that it is to use your influence, such as it is, on behalf of the right against the wrong, as far as you can tell the right from the wrong. You can lay down all these general principles, but that is not a policy. Surely, if you are to have a policy you must take the particular situations and consider what action or inaction is suitable for those particular situations. That is what I myself mean by policy, and it is quite clear that as the situations and conditions in foreign affairs continually change from day to day, your policy cannot be stated once and for all, if it is to be applicable to every situation that arises.25

The intellectual superiority of the Left is seldom in doubt. The Left alone thinks out principles of political action and evolves ideals for statesmen to aim at. But it lacks practical experience which comes from close contact with reality. In Great Britain after 1919, it was a serious misfortune that the Left, having enjoyed office for negligible periods, had little experience of administrative realities and became more and more a party of pure theory, while the Right, having spent so little time in opposition, had few temptations to pit the perfection of theory against the imperfections of practice. In Soviet Russia, the group in power is more and more discarding theory in favour of practice as it loses the memory of its revolutionary origin. History everywhere shows that, when Left parties or politicians are brought into contact with reality through the assumption of political office, they tend to abandon their ‘doctrinaire’ utopianism and move towards the Right, often retaining their Left labels and thereby adding to the confusion of political terminology.

Ethics and politics

Most fundamental of all, the antithesis of utopia and reality is rooted in a different conception of the relationship of politics and ethics. The antithesis between the world of value and the world of nature, already implicit in the dichotomy of purpose and fact, is deeply embedded in the human consciousness and in political thought. The utopian sets up an ethical standard which purports to be independent of politics, and seeks to make politics conform to it. The realist cannot logically accept any standard value save that of fact. In his view, the absolute standard of the utopian is conditioned and dictated by the social order, and is therefore political. Morality can only be relative, not universal. Ethics must be interpreted in terms of politics; and the search for an ethical norm outside politics is doomed to frustration. The identification of the supreme reality with the supreme good, which Christianity achieves by a bold stroke of dogmatism, is achieved by the realist through the assumption that there is no good other than the acceptance and understanding of reality.

These implications of the opposition between utopia and reality will emerge clearly from a more detailed study of the modern crisis in international politics.

Notes

1.

|   |

A. Sorel, L’Europe et la Révolution Française, p. 474.

2.

|   |

The psychologist may be interested to trace here an analogy – it would be dangerous to treat it as more – with Jung’s classification of psychological types as ‘introverted’ and ‘extraverted’ (Jung, Psychological Types) or William James’s pairs of opposites: Rationalist-Empiricist, Intellectualist-Sensationalist, Idealist-Materialist, Optimistic-Pessimistic, Religious-Irreligious, Free-willist-Fatalistic, Monistic-Pluralistic, Dogmatical-Sceptical (W. James, Pragmatism).

3.

|   |

League of Nations: Sixteenth Assembly, p. 72.

4.

|   |

Angell, The Great Illusion, p. 138.

5.

|   |

Similarly, Marx’s theory of surplus value has, in the words of a sympathetic critic, ‘rather the significance of a political and social slogan than of an economic truth’ (M. Beer, The Life and Teaching of Karl Marx, p. 129).

6.

|   |

Having discovered that other states were perhaps more open to attack than themselves, the Soviet authorities in May 1939 dismissed Mr Litvinov and ceased to talk about the indivisibility of peace.

7.

|   |

The term ‘bureaucrat’ may be taken for this purpose to include those members of the fighting services who are concerned with the direction of policy. It is, perhaps, unnecessary to add that not every possessor of an intellect is an intellectual, or every occupant of a desk in a government department a bureaucrat. There are, nevertheless, modes of thought which are, broadly speaking, characteristic of the ‘bureaucrat’ and the ‘intellectual’ respectively.

8.

|   |

R. S. Baker, Woodrow Wilson: Life and Letters, iii. p. 90.

9.

|   |

Meinecke, Staat und Perso"nlicbkeit, p. 136.

10.

|   |

Lenin, Works (2nd Russian ed.), vii. p. 72.

11.

|   |

Mannheim, Ideology and Utopia, pp. 137–40.

12.

|   |

League of Nations: Fifteenth Assembly, Sixth Committee, p. 62.

13.

|   |

Bryce, Modern Democracies, i. p. 89.

14.

|   |

Quoted in Lenin, Works (2nd Russian ed.), iv. p. 381.

15.

|   |

‘We possess the most theoretical labour movement in the world’ (F. Naumann, Central Europe, Engl. transl., p. 121).

16.

|   |

This interpretation, which appears in Mirsky’s Lenin (pp. III, 117–18) published in 1931, received further confirmation from subsequent events. The rift went back to the earliest days of the party. In 1904 Lenin was attacking the party intellectuals for their neglect of discipline and organization, and the intellectuals were attacking Lenin’s bureaucratic methods (Lenin, Works (2nd Russian ed.), vi. pp. 309–11).

17.

|   |

R. S. Baker, Woodrow Wilson and World Settlement, i. p. 112.

18.

|   |

History of the Peace Conference, ed. H. Temperley, iii. p. 62.

19.

|   |

House of Commons, 21 July 1919: Official Report, col. 993.

20.

|   |

League of Nations: Second Assembly, Third Committee, p. 281.

21.

|   |

‘It is not to be tolerated’, said the Belgian socialist De Brouckère, ‘that the people should be robbed of their hopes of peace by experts who are losing themselves in the maze of technicalities which, with a little goodwill, might be disentangled in a few hours’ (Peace and Disarmament Committee of the Women’s International Organisations: Circular of 15 May 1932). About the same time, Lord Cecil was reported in the same sense: ‘If the matter was to be left to experts nothing would be done. They were, he was sure, most able, conscientious, highly instructed gentlemen, but just look at their training’ (Manchester Guardian, 18 May 1932).

22.

|   |

Moeller van den Bruck, Das Dritte Reich (3rd ed.), p. 257.

23.

|   |

Baldwin, On England, p. 153.

24.

|   |

Winston Churchill, Step by Step, p. 147.

25.

|   |

House of Commons, 21 October 1937, reprinted in N. Chamberlain, The Struggle for Peace, p. 33.

CHAPTER SEVEN

The Nature of Politics

Man has always lived in groups. The smallest kind of human group, the family, has clearly been necessary for the maintenance of the species. But so far as is known, men have always from the most primitive times formed semi-permanent groups larger than the single family; and one of the functions of such a group has been to regulate relations between its members. Politics deals with the behaviour of men in such organized permanent or semi-permanent groups. All attempts to deduce the nature of society from the supposed behaviour of man in isolation are purely theoretical, since there is no reason to assume that such a man ever existed. Aristotle laid the foundation of all sound thinking about politics when he declared that man was by nature a political animal.

Man in society reacts to his fellow men in two opposite ways. Sometimes he displays egoism, or the will to assert himself at the expense of others. At other times he displays sociability, or the desire to co-operate with others, to enter into reciprocal relations of good will and friendship with them, and even to subordinate himself to them. In every society, these two qualities can be seen at work. No society can exist unless a substantial proportion of its members exhibits in some degree the desire for co-operation and mutual good will. But in every society some sanction is required to produce the measure of solidarity requisite for its maintenance; and this sanction is applied by a controlling group or individual acting in the name of the society. Membership of most societies is voluntary, and the only ultimate sanction which can be applied is expulsion. But the peculiarity of political society, which in the modern world takes the form of the state, is that membership is compulsory. The state, like other societies, must be based on some sense of common interests and obligations among its members. But coercion is regularly exercised by a governing group to enforce loyalty and obedience; and this coercion inevitably means that the governors control the governed and ‘exploit’ them for their own purposes.1

The dual character of political society is therefore strongly marked. Professor Laski tells us that ‘every state is built upon the consciences of men’.2 On the other hand, anthropology, as well as much recent history, teaches that ‘war seems to be the main agency in producing the state’;3 and Professor Laski himself, in another passage, declares that ‘our civilization is held together by fear rather than by good will’.4 There is no contradiction between these apparently opposite views. When Tom Paine, in the Rights of Man, tries to confront Burke with the dilemma that ‘governments arise either out of the people or over the people’, the answer is that they do both. Coercion and conscience, enmity and good will, self-assertion and self-subordination, are present in every political society. The state is built up out of these two conflicting aspects of human nature. Utopia and reality, the ideal and the institution, morality and power, are from the outset inextricably blended in it. In the making of the United States, as a modern American writer has said, ‘Hamilton stood for strength, wealth and power, Jefferson for the American dream’; and both the power and the dream were necessary ingredients.5

If this be correct, we can draw one important conclusion. The utopian who dreams that it is possible to eliminate self-assertion from politics and to base a political system on morality alone is just as wide of the mark as the realist who believes that altruism is an illusion and that all political action is based on self-seeking. These errors have both left their mark on popular terminology. The phrase ‘power politics’ is often used in an invidious sense, as if the element of power or self-assertion in politics were something abnormal and susceptible of elimination from a healthy political life. Conversely, there is a disposition, even among some writers who are not strictly speaking realists, to treat politics as the science of power and self-assertion and exclude from it by definition actions inspired by the moral consciousness. Professor Catlin describes the homo politicus as one who ‘seeks to bring into conformity with his own will the wills of others, so that he may the better attain his own ends’.6 Such terminological implications are misleading. Politics cannot be divorced from power. But the homo politicus who pursues nothing but power is as unreal a myth as the homo economicus who pursues nothing but gain. Political action must be based on a co-ordination of morality and power.

This truth is of practical as well as theoretical importance. It is as fatal in politics to ignore power as it is to ignore morality. The fate of China in the nineteenth century is an illustration of what happens to a country which is content to believe in the moral superiority of its own civilization and to despise the ways of power. The Liberal Government of Great Britain nearly came to grief in the spring of 1914 because it sought to pursue an Irish policy based on moral authority unsupported (or rather, directly opposed) by effective military power. In Germany, the Frankfort Assembly of 1848 is the classic example of the impotence of ideas divorced from power; and the Weimar Republic broke down because many of the policies it pursued – in fact, nearly all of them except its opposition to the communists – were unsupported, or actively opposed, by effective military power.7 The utopian, who believes that democracy is not based on force, refuses to look these unwelcome facts in the face.

On the other hand, the realist, who believes that, if you look after the power, the moral authority will look after itself, is equally in error. The most recent form of this doctrine is embodied in the much-quoted phrase: ‘The function of force is to give moral ideas times to take root’. Internationally, this argument was used in 1919 by those who, unable to defend the Versailles Treaty on moral grounds, maintained that this initial act of power would pave the way for subsequent moral appeasement. Experience has done little to confirm this comfortable belief. The same fallacy is implicit in the once popular view that the aim of British policy should be ‘to rebuild the League of Nations, to make it capable of holding a political aggressor in restraint by armed power, and thereafter to labour faithfully for the mitigation of just and real grievances’.8 Once the enemy has been crushed or the ‘aggressor’ restrained by force, the ‘thereafter’ fails to arrive. The illusion that priority can be given to power and that morality will follow, is just as dangerous as the illusion that priority can be given to moral authority and that power will follow.

Before proceeding, however, to consider the respective roles of power and morality in politics, we must take some note of the views of those who, though far from being realists, identify politics with power and believe that moral concepts must be altogether excluded from its scope. There is, according to this view, an essential antinomy between politics and morality; and the moral man as such will therefore have nothing to do with politics. This thesis has many attractions, and reappears at different periods of history and in different contexts. It takes at least three forms.

(i) Its simplest form is the doctrine of non-resistance. The moral man recognizes the existence of political power as an evil, but regards the use of power to resist power as a still greater evil. This is the basis of such doctrines of non-resistance as those of Jesus or of Gandhi, or of modern pacifism. It amounts, in brief, to a boycott of politics.

(ii) The second form of the antithesis between politics and morality is anarchism. The state, as the principal organ of political power, is ‘the most flagrant, most cynical and most complete negation of humanity’.9 The anarchist will use power to overthrow the state. This revolutionary power is, however, not thought of as political power, but as the spontaneous revolt of the outraged individual conscience. It does not seek to create a new political society to take the place of the old one, but a moral society from which power, and consequently politics, are completely eliminated. ‘The principles of the Sermon on the Mount’, an English divine recently remarked, would mean ‘sudden death to civilised society’.10 The anarchist sets out to destroy ‘civilised society’ in the name of the Sermon on the Mount.

(iii) A third school of thought starts from the same premise of the essential antithesis between morality and politics, but arrives at a totally different conclusion. The injunction of Jesus to ‘render unto Caesar the things that are Caesar’s, and unto God the things that are God’s’, implies the co-existence of two separate spheres: the political and the moral. But the moral man is under an obligation to assist – or at any rate not to obstruct – the politician in the discharge of his non-moral functions. ‘Let every soul be subject to the higher powers. The powers that be are ordained of God.’ We thus recognize politics as necessary but non-moral. This tradition, which remained dormant throughout the Middle Ages, when the ecclesiastical and the secular authority was theoretically one, was revived by Luther in order to effect his compromise between reformed church and state. Luther ‘turned on the peasants of his day in holy horror when they attempted to transmute the “spiritual” kingdom into an “earthly” one by suggesting that the principles of the gospel had social significance.’11 The division of functions between Caesar and God is implicit in the very conception of an ‘established’ church. But the tradition has been more persistent and more effective in Lutheran Germany than anywhere else. ‘We do not consult Jesus’, wrote a German liberal nineteenth-century pastor, ‘when we are concerned with things which belong to the domain of the construction of the state and political economy’;12 and Bernhardi declared that ‘Christian morality is personal and social, and in its nature cannot be political’.13 The same attitude is inherent in the modern theology of Karl Barth, which insists that political and social evils are the necessary product of man’s sinful nature and that human effort to eradicate them is therefore futile; and the doctrine that Christian morality has nothing to do with politics is vigorously upheld by the Nazi régime. This view is basically different from that of the realist who makes morality a function of politics. But in the field of politics it tends to become indistinguishable from realism.

The theory of the divorce between the spheres of politics and morality is superficially attractive, if only because it evades the insoluble problem of finding a moral justification for the use of force.14 But it is not ultimately satisfying. Both non-resistance and anarchism are counsels of despair, which appear to find widespread acceptance only where men feel hopeless of achieving anything by political action; and the attempt to keep God and Caesar in watertight compartments runs too much athwart the deep-seated desire of the human mind to reduce its view of the world to some kind of moral order. We are not in the long run satisfied to believe that what is politically good is morally bad;15 and since we can neither moralize power nor expel power from politics, we are faced with a dilemma which cannot be completely resolved. The planes of utopia and of reality never coincide. The ideal cannot be institutionalized, nor the institution idealized. ‘Politics’, writes Dr Niebuhr, ‘will, to the end of history, be an area where conscience and power meet, where the ethical and coercive factors of human life will interpenetrate and work out their tentative and uneasy compromises.’16 The compromises, like solutions of other human problems, will remain uneasy and tentative. But it is an essential part of any compromise that both factors shall be taken into account.

We have now therefore to analyse the part played in international politics by these two cardinal factors: power and morality.

Notes

1.

|   |

‘Everywhere do I perceive a certain conspiracy of the rich men seeking their own advantage under the name and pretext of the commonwealth’ (More, Utopia). ‘The exploitation of one part of society by another is common to all past centuries’ (Communist Manifesto).

2.

|   |

A Defence of Liberty against Tyrants (Vindiciae contra Tyrannos), ed. Laski, Introd., p. 55.

3.

|   |

Linton, The Study of Man, p. 240.

4.

|   |

Laski, A Grammar of Politics, p. 20.

5.

|   |

J. Truslow Adams, The Epic of America, p. 112. The idea that the state has a moral foundation in the consent of its citizens as well as a power foundation was propounded by Locke and Rousseau and popularized by the American and French revolutions. Two recent expressions of the idea may be quoted. The Czecho-Slovak declaration of independence of 18 October 1918 described Austria-Hungary as ‘a state which has no justification for its existence, and which, since it refuses to accept the fundamental basis of modern world-organisation [i.e. self-determination], is only an artificial and unmoral construction’. In February 1938, Hitler told Schuschnigg, the then Austrian Chancellor, that ‘a régime lacking every kind of legality and which in reality ruled only by force, must in the long run come into continually increasing conflict with public opinion’ (speech in the Reichstag of 17 March 1938). Hitler maintained that the two pillars of the state are ‘force’ and ‘popularity’ (Mein Kampf, p. 579).

6.

|   |

Catlin, The Science and Method of Politics, p. 309.

7.

|   |

It is significant that the word Realpolitik was coined in the once famous treatise of von Rochau, Grundsatze der Realpolitik published in 1853, which was largely inspired by the lessons of Frankfort. The inspiration which Hiter’s Realpolitik has derived from the lessons of the Weimar Republic is obvious.

8.

|   |

Winston Churchill, Arms and the Covenant, p. 368. The argument that power is a necessary motive force for the remedy of ‘just’ grievances is further developed on pp. 209–16.

9.

|   |

Bakunin, (Oeuvres, i. p. 150; cf. vi. p. 17: ‘If there is a devil in all human history, it is this principle of command and authority.’

10.

|   |

The Dean of St Paul’s quoted in a leading article in The Times, 2 August 1937.

11.

|   |

R. Niebuhr, Moral Man and Immoral Society, p. 77.

12.

|   |

Quoted in W. F. Bruck, Social and Economic History of Germany, p. 65.

13.

|   |

Bernhardi, Germany and the Next War (Engl. transl.), p. 29.

14.

|   |

‘Force in the right place’, as Mr Maxton once said in the House of Commons, is a meaningless conception, ‘because the right place for me is exactly where I want to use it, and for him also, and for everyone else’ (House of Commons, 7 November 1933: Official Record, col. 130). Force in politics is always the instrument of some kind of group interest.

15.

|   |

Acton was fond of saying that ‘great men are almost always bad men’, and quotes Walpole’s dictum that ‘no great country was ever saved by good men’ (History of Freedom, p. 219). Rosebery showed more acuteness when he remarked that ‘there is one question which English people ask about great men: Was he “a good man”?’ (Napoleon: The Last Phase, p. 364).

16.

|   |

R. Niebuhr, Moral Man and Immoral Society, p. 4.

CHAPTER EIGHT

Power in International Politics

Politics are, then, in one sense always power politics. Common usage applies the term ‘political’ not to all activities of the state, but to issues involving a conflict of power. Once this conflict has been resolved, the issue ceases to be ‘political’ and becomes a matter of administrative routine. Nor is all business transacted between states ‘political’. When states cooperate with one another to maintain postal or transport services, or to prevent the spread of epidemics or suppress the traffic in drugs, these activities are described as ‘non-political’ or ‘technical’. But as soon as an issue arises which involves, or is thought to involve, the power of one state in relation to another, the matter at once becomes ‘political’. While politics cannot be satisfactorily defined exclusively in terms of power, it is safe to say that power is always an essential element of politics. In order to understand a political issue, it is not enough (as it would be in the case of a technical or a legal issue) to know what the point at issue is. It is necessary also to know between whom it has arisen. An issue raised by a small number of isolated individuals is not the same political fact as the same issue raised by a powerful and well-organized trade union. A political issue arising between Great Britain and Japan is something quite different from what may be formally the same issue between Great Britain and Nicaragua. ‘Politics begin where the masses are,’ said Lenin, ‘not where there are thousands, but where there are millions, that is where serious politics begin.’1

There have been periods of history when it might have been superfluous to dwell on this obvious fact, and when Engels’ dictum that ‘without force and iron ruthlessness nothing is achieved in history’2 would have passed as a platitude. But in the comparatively well-ordered world of nineteenth-century liberalism, subtler forms of compulsion successfully concealed from the unsophisticated the continuous but silent workings of political power; and in democracies, at any rate, this concealment is still partially effective.3 After the first world war, the liberal tradition was carried into international politics. Utopian writers from the English-speaking countries seriously believed that the establishment of the League of Nations meant the elimination of power from international relations, and the substitution of discussion for armies and navies. ‘Power politics’ were regarded as a mark of the bad old times, and became a term of abuse. That this belief should have persisted for more than ten years was due to the circumstance that the Great Powers whose main interest was the preservation of the status quo enjoyed throughout that time a virtual monopoly of power. A game of chess between a world champion and a schoolboy would be so rapidly and so effortlessly won that the innocent onlooker might be pardoned for assuming that little skill was necessary to play chess. In the same way, the simple-minded spectator of the game of international politics could assume, between 1920 and 1931, that power played little part in the game. What was commonly called the ‘return to power politics’ in 1931was, in fact, the termination of the monopoly of power enjoyed by the status quo Powers. Stalin’s lament that ‘in our days it is not the custom to reckon with the weak’, and Neville Chamberlain’s remark that ‘in the world as we find it today an unarmed nation has little chance of making its voice heard’,4 were curious tributes – more surprising in the professed Marxist than in the inheritor of a British nineteenth-century tradition – to the illusion that there was once a time when weak and unarmed countries played an effective role in international politics.

The assumption of the elimination of power from politics could only result from a wholly uncritical attitude towards political problems. In the affairs of the League of Nations, formal equality and the participation of all in debate did not render the power factor any less decisive. The founders of the League themselves entertained no such illusion. House originally thought that only Great Powers should be admitted to the League at all.5 In the earliest British and American drafts of the Covenant, it was contemplated that membership of the Council of the League would be limited to Great Powers; and Lord Cecil noted on one of these drafts that ‘the smaller Powers would in any case not exercise any considerable influence’.6 This prevision was fulfilled. An Italian delegate testified that during the long period of his regular attendances at Geneva he ‘never saw a dispute of any importance settled otherwise than by an agreement between the Great Powers’, and that the procedure of the League was ‘a system of detours, all of which lead to one or other of these two issues: agreement or disagreement between Great Britain, Italy, France and Germany’.7 ‘Despite our juridical equality here,’ said Mr De Valera a little later, ‘in matters such as European peace the small states are powerless.’8 The decisions on the application of sanctions against Italy in the winter of 1935–36 were, in effect, taken solely by Great Britain and France, the possessorsofeffectivemilitaryandeconomicpowerintheMediterranean. The minor Powers followed their lead; and one of them was actually ‘compensated’ by Great Britain and France for so doing.

Nor was it only at Geneva that the weak Powers set their course to match that of the strong. When Great Britain took her currency off the gold standard in September 1931, several minor Powers were obliged to follow her example. When France abandoned the gold standard in September 1936, Switzerland and Holland – the last free gold countries – were compelled to follow suit, and several other smaller countries had to alter the value of their currencies. When France was militarily supreme in Europe in the nineteen-twenties, a number of smaller Powers grouped themselves under her aegis. When German military strength eclipsed that of France, most of these Powers made declarations of neutrality or veered to the side of Germany. The alleged ‘dictatorship of the Great Powers’, which is sometimes denounced by utopian writers as if it were a wicked policy deliberately adopted by certain states, is a fact which constitutes something like a ‘law of nature’ in international politics.

It is necessary at this point to dispel the current illusion that the policy of those states which are, broadly speaking, satisfied with the status quo and whose watchword is ‘security’, is somehow less concerned with power than the policy of the dissatisfied states, and that the popular phrase ‘power politics’ applies to the acts of the latter but not to those of the former. This illusion, which has an almost irresistible attraction for the publicists of the satisfied Powers, is responsible for much confused thinking about international politics. The pursuit of ‘security’ by satisfied Powers has often been the motive of flagrant examples of power politics. In order to secure themselves against the revenge of a defeated enemy, victorious Powers have in the past resorted to such measures as the taking of hostages, the mutilation or enslavement of males of military age or, in modern times, the dismemberment and occupation of territory or forced disarmament. It is profoundly misleading to represent the struggle between satisfied and dissatisfied Powers as a struggle between morality on one side and power on the other. It is a clash in which, whatever the moral issue, power politics are equally predominant on both sides.

The history of the Locarno Treaty is a simple and revealing illustration of the working of power politics. The first proposal for a treaty guaranteeing Germany’s western frontier was made by Germany in December 1922, and was emphatically rejected by Poincare’. At this period (it was the eve of the Ruhr invasion), Germany had everything to fear from France, and France nothing to fear from a helpless Germany; and the treaty had no attraction for France. Two years later the position had changed. The Ruhr invasion had brought little profit to France, and had left her perplexed as to the next step. Germany might one day be powerful again. Germany, on the other hand, still feared the military supremacy of France, and hankered after a guarantee. It was the psychological moment when French fear of Germany was about equally balanced by Germany’s fear of France; and a treaty which had not been possible two years before, and would not have been possible five years later, was now welcome to both. Moreover, the power interests of Great Britain coincided with those of Germany. Germany had abandoned hope of securing a revision of her western, but not of her other, frontiers. Great Britain was prepared to guarantee Germany’s western, but not her other, frontiers. Germany, anxious to expedite the withdrawal of the Allied army from the Rhineland, had as yet no hope of breaking down the restrictions imposed by the demilitarization clauses of the Versailles Treaty; and she was therefore quite prepared to purchase the new agreement by reaffirming her acceptance of those clauses and placing them under a guarantee.

Such was the background of the famous Locarno Treaty. Its success was a striking one. For years afterwards, attempts were made to repeat it in other fields. Mediterranean and Eastern European ‘Locarnos’ were canvassed; and their failure to materialize disappointed and puzzled people who believed that international problems everywhere could be solved by devices of the same standard pattern, and who failed to understand that the Locarno Treaty was an expression of the power politics of a particular period and locality. Ten years after its conclusion, the delicate balance on which it rested had disappeared. France feared Germany more than ever. But Germany no longer feared anything from France. The treaty no longer had any meaning for Germany save as an affirmation of the demilitarization clauses of the Versailles Treaty which she could now hope to overthrow. The only part of the Locarno Treaty which still corresponded to the situation of power politics was the British guarantee to France and Belgium. This was repeated by Great Britain after the rest of the treaty had been denounced by Germany. The history of Locarno is a classic instance of power politics. It remains incomprehensible to those who seek uniform a priori solutions of the problem of security, and regard power politics as an abnormal phenomenon visible only in periods of crisis.

Failure to recognize that power is an essential element of politics has hitherto vitiated all attempts to establish international forms of government, and confused nearly every attempt to discuss the subject. Power is an indispensable instrument of government. To internationalize government in any real sense means to internationalize power; and international government is, in effect, government by that state which supplies the power necessary for the purpose of governing. The international governments set up by the Versailles Treaty in various parts of Europe were temporary in character, and had not therefore to face the problems of a long-term policy. But even these illustrate the intimate connexion between government and power. The Inter-Allied High Commission, which exercised in the occupied Rhineland such functions of government as were necessary for the security of the Allied troops, worked smoothly so long as British and French policies coincided. When the Ruhr crisis caused a serious difference of opinion between the British and French Governments, French policy was applied in the zones occupied by French and Belgian troops and British policy in the zone occupied by British troops, the policy of the government being determined by the nationality of the power on which it rested. The Inter-Allied Commission appointed to conduct the plebiscite in Upper Silesia pursued the French policy of favouring Poland so long as the Allied troops on which its authority depended were supplied almost exclusively by France. This policy was corrected only when British troops were sent to the area. The effective control of any government depends on the source of its power.

The problem of international government and power was raised in a more acute form by the mandates system and by the proposal frequently put forward that the government of some or all colonial territories shall be ‘internationalized’. We are here faced by an issue of permanent government, involving the formulation of long-term policy, and different in kind from that of temporary international collaboration between allies under stress of war or for the purpose of implementing a treaty jointly imposed. Its nature may be illustrated from the case of Palestine. Policy in Palestine was dependent on the amount of military force available for use there, and had therefore to be determined not by the Mandates Commission, which had no power at its disposal, but by the British Government, which supplies the power; for whatever view might be taken by the Mandates Commission, it was unthinkable that British troops could be used to carry out a policy of which the British Government or the British electorate did not approve.9 Under any international system of government, policy would depend, at critical moments, on the decision of the state supplying the power on which the authority of the government depended. If, as would almost inevitably happen, the control of an international territory were divided geographically among the forces of different states, the different zones would, in periods of international discord, pursue discordant policies: and the old international rivalries would recur in a new and equally dangerous form. Problems of economic development would be not less baffling. The international administration of colonial areas, wrote Lugard, himself an experienced and enlightened administrator, ‘would paralyse all initiative by the dead hand of a super-bureaucracy devoid of national sentiment and stifling to all patriotism, and would be very disadvantageous to the countries concerned’.10 Any real international government is impossible so long as power, which is an essential condition of government, is organized nationally. The international secretariat of the League of Nations was able to function precisely because it was a non-political civil service, had no responsibility for policy, and was therefore independent of power.

Political power in the international sphere may be divided, for purposes of discussion, into three categories: (a) military power, (b) economic power, (c) power over opinion. We shall find, however, that these categories are closely interdependent; and though they are theoretically separable, it is difficult in practice to imagine a country for any length of time possessing one kind of power in isolation from the others. In its essence, power is an indivisible whole. ‘The laws of social dynamics’, a recent critic has said, ‘are laws which can only be stated in terms of power, not in terms of this or that form of power.’11

(a) Military power

The supreme importance of the military instrument lies in the fact that the ultima ratio of power in international relations is war. Every act of the state, in its power aspect, is directed to war, not as a desirable weapon, but as a weapon which it may require in the last resort to use. Clausewitz’s famous aphorism that ‘war is nothing but the continuation of political relations by other means’ has been repeated with approval both by Lenin and by the Communist International;12 and Hitler meant much the same thing when he said that ‘an alliance whose object does not include the intention to fight is meaningless and useless’.13 In the same sense, Mr Hawtrey defines diplomacy as ‘potential war’.14 These are half-truths. But the important thing is to recognize that they are true. War lurks in the background of international politics just as revolution lurks in the background of domestic politics. There are few European countries where, at some time during the past thirty years, potential revolution has not been an important factor in politics;15 and the international community has in this respect the closest analogy to those states where the possibility of revolution is most frequently and most conspicuously present to the mind.

Potential war being thus a dominant factor in international politics, military strength becomes a recognized standard of political values. Every great civilization of the past has enjoyed in its day a superiority of military power. The Greek city-state rose to greatness when its hoplite armies proved more than a match for the Persian hordes. In the modern world, Powers (the word itself is significant enough) are graded according to the quality and the supposed efficiency of the military equipment, including manpower, at their disposal. Recognition as a Great Power is normally the reward of fighting a successful large-scale war. Germany after the Franco-Prussian War, the United States after the war with Spain, and Japan after the Russo-Japanese War are familiar recent instances. The faint doubt attaching to Italy’s status as a Great Power is partly due to the fact that she has never proved her prowess in a first-class war. Any symptom of military inefficiency or unpreparedness in a Great Power is promptly reflected in its political status. The naval mutiny at Invergordon in September 1931 was the final blow to British prestige which compelled Great Britain to devalue her currency. The execution of the leading Soviet generals for alleged treason in June 1937 was thought to reveal so much weakness in the Soviet military machine that the political influence of Soviet Russia suffered a sudden and severe slump. Statesmen of all the Great Powers periodically make speeches extolling the efficiency of their armies, navies and air forces; and military parades and reviews are organized in order to impress the world with the military strength and consequent political standing of the nation. In international crises, fleets, troops or air squadrons show themselves conspicuously at crucial points for the same purpose.

These facts point to the moral that foreign policy never can, or never should, be divorced from strategy. The foreign policy of a country is limited not only by its aims, but also by its military strength or, more accurately, by the ratio of its military strength to that of other countries. The most serious problem involved in the democratic control of foreign policy is that no government can afford to divulge full and frank information about its own military strength, or all the knowledge it possesses about the military strength of other countries. Public discussions of foreign policy are therefore conducted in partial or total ignorance of one of the factors which must be decisive in determining it. A constitutional rule of long standing precludes private members of Parliament from proposing motions which entail public expenditure. The same restraint might well be exercised in advocating policies which entail risk of war; for only the government and its advisers can assess the chances with anything like complete knowledge of the relevant facts. Many contemporary books and speeches about international politics are reminiscent of those ingenious mathematical problems which the student is invited to solve by ignoring the weight of the elephant. The solutions proposed are neat and accurate on the abstract plane, but are obtained by leaving out of account the vital strategic factor. Even so important, and in many ways so valuable, a work as the annual Survey of International Affairs frequently soars into the realms of fancy when it embarks on criticism of policy, precisely because it neglects those military limitations which are always present to the minds of those who have to solve problems of foreign policy in real life. If every prospective writer on international affairs in the last twenty years had taken a compulsory course in elementary strategy, reams of nonsense would have remained unwritten.

Military power, being an essential element in the life of the state, becomes not only an instrument, but an end in itself. Few of the important wars of the last hundred years seem to have been waged for the deliberate and conscious purpose of increasing either trade or territory. The most serious wars are fought in order to make one’s own country militarily stronger or, more often, to prevent another country from becoming militarily stronger, so that there is much justification for the epigram that ‘the principal cause of war is war itself’.16 Every stage of the Napoleonic Wars was devised to prepare the way for the next stage: the invasion of Russia was undertaken in order to make Napoleon strong enough to defeat Great Britain. The Crimean War was waged by Great Britain and France in order to prevent Russia from becoming strong enough to attack their Near Eastern possessions and interests at some future time. The origin of the Russo-Japanese War of 1904–5 is described as follows in a note addressed to the League of Nations by the Soviet Government in 1924: ‘When the Japanese torpedo-boats attacked the Russian fleet at Port Arthur in 1904, it was clearly an act of aggression from a technical point of view, but, politically speaking, it was an act caused by the aggressive policy of the Tsarist Government towards Japan, who, in order to forestall the danger, struck the first blow at her adversary.’17 In 1914, Austria sent an ultimatum to Serbia because she believed that Serbians were planning the downfall of the Dual Monarchy; Russia feared that Austria-Hungary, if she defeated Serbia, would be strong enough to menace her; Germany feared that Russia, if she defeated Austria-Hungary, would be strong enough to menace her; France had long believed that Germany, if she defeated Russia, would be strong enough to menace her, and had therefore concluded the Franco-Russian alliance; and Great Britain feared that Germany, if she defeated France and occupied Belgium, would be strong enough to menace her. Finally, the United States came to fear that Germany, if she won the war, would be strong enough to menace them. Thus the war, in the minds of all the principal combatants, had a defensive or preventive character. They fought in order that they might not find themselves in a more unfavourable position in some future war. Even colonial acquisitions have often been prompted by the same motive. The consolidation and formal annexation of the original British settlements in Australia were inspired by fear of Napoleon’s alleged design to establish French colonies there. Military, rather than economic, reasons dictated the capture of German colonies during the war of 1914 and afterwards precluded their return to Germany.

It is perhaps for this reason that the exercise of power always appears to beget the appetite for more power. There is, as Dr Niebuhr says, ‘no possibility of drawing a sharp line between the will-to-live and the will-to-power’.18 Nationalism, having attained its first objective in the form of national unity and independence, develops almost automatically into imperialism. International politics amply confirm the aphorisms of Machiavelli that ‘men never appear to themselves to possess securely what they have unless they acquire something further from another’,19 and of Hobbes that man ‘cannot assure the power and means to live well which he hath present, without the acquisition of more’.20 Wars, begun for motives of security, quickly become wars of aggression and self-seeking. President McKinley invited the United States to intervene in Cuba against Spain in order ‘to secure a full and final termination of hostilities between the Government of Spain and the people of Cuba and to secure on the island the establishment of a stable government’.21 But by the time the war was over the temptation to self-aggrandizement by the annexation of the Philippines had become irresistible. Nearly every country participating in the first world war regarded it initially as a war of self-defence; and this belief was particularly strong on the Allied side. Yet during the course of the war, every Allied Government in Europe announced war aims which included the acquisition of territory from the enemy Powers. In modern conditions, wars of limited objective have become almost as impossible as wars of limited liability. It is one of the fallacies of the theory of collective security that war can be waged for the specific and disinterested purpose of ‘resisting aggression’. Had the League of Nations in the autumn of 1935, under the leadership of Great Britain, embarked on ‘military sanctions’ against Italy, it would have been impossible to restrict the campaign to the expulsion of Italian troops from Abyssinia. Operations would in all probability have led to the occupation of Italy’s East African colonies by Great Britain and France, of Trieste, Fiume and Albania by Yugoslavia, and of the islands of the Dodecanese by Greece or Turkey or both; and war aims would have been announced, precluding on various specious grounds the restoration of these territories to Italy. Territorial ambitions are just as likely to be the product as the cause of war.

(b) Economic power

Economic strength has always been an instrument of political power, if only through its association with the military instrument. Only the most primitive kinds of warfare are altogether independent of the economic factor. The wealthiest prince or the wealthiest city-state could hire the largest and most efficient army of mercenaries; and every government was therefore compelled to pursue a policy designed to further the acquisition of wealth. The whole progress of civilization has been so closely bound up with economic development that we are not surprised to trace, throughout modern history, an increasingly intimate association between military and economic power. In the prolonged conflicts which marked the close of the Middle Ages in Western Europe, the merchants of the towns, relying on organized economic power, defeated the feudal barons, who put their trust in individual military prowess. The rise of modern nations has everywhere been marked by the emergence of a new middle class economically based on industry and trade. Trade and finance were the foundation of the shortlived political supremacy of the Italian cities of the Renaissance and later of the Dutch. The principal international wars of the period from the Renaissance to the middle of the eighteenth century were trade wars (some of them were actually so named). Throughout this period, it was universally held that, since wealth is a source of political power, the state should seek actively to promote the acquisition of wealth; and it was believed that the right way to make a country powerful was to stimulate production at home, to buy as little as possible from abroad, and to accumulate wealth in the convenient form of precious metals. Those who argued in this way afterwards came to be known as mercantilists. Mercantilism was a system of economic policy based on the hitherto unquestioned assumption that to promote the acquisition of wealth was part of the normal function of the state.

The separation of economics from politics

The laissez-faire doctrine of the classical economists made a frontal attack on this assumption. The principal implications of laissez-faire have already been discussed. Its significance in the present context is that it brought about a complete theoretical divorce between economics and politics. The classical economists conceived a natural economic order with laws of its own, independent of politics and functioning to the greatest profit of all concerned when political authority interfered least in its automatic operation. This doctrine dominated the economic thought, and to some extent the economic practice (though far more in Great Britain than elsewhere), of the nineteenth century. The theory of the nineteenth-century liberal state presupposed the existence side by side of two separate systems. The political system, which was the sphere of government, was concerned with the maintenance of law and order and the provision of certain essential services, and was thought of mainly as a necessary evil. The economic system, which was the preserve of private enterprise, catered for the material wants and, in doing so, organized the everyday lives of the great mass of the citizens.22 In current English theory, the doctrine of the separation of politics and economics was sometimes carried to astonishing lengths. ‘Is it true’, asked Sir Normal Angell shortly before the first world war, ‘that wealth and prosperity and well-being depend on the political power of nations, or indeed that one has anything whatever to do with the other?’23 And the whole argument depends on the confident assumption that every intelligent reader will answer in the negative. As late as 1915, an English philosopher detected ‘an ineradicable tendency that, as wealth and its control and enjoyment go to the productive class, so power and prestige go to the professional class’, and regarded this separation of economic from political power as not only ineradicable but ‘essential to a decent society’.24

Even before 1900, a more penetrating analysis might have shown that the illusion of a divorce between politics and economics was fast breaking down. It is still open to debate whether late nineteenth-century imperialism should be regarded as an economic movement using political weapons, or as a political movement using economic weapons. But that economics and politics marched hand in hand towards the same objective is clear enough. ‘Is it not precisely the hallmark of British statesmanship’, asked Hitler, ‘to draw economic advantages from political strength, and to transform every economic gain back into political power?’25 The first world war, by overtly reuniting economics and politics, in both domestic and foreign policy, hastened a development which was already on the way. It was now revealed that the nineteenth century, while purporting to take economics altogether out of the political sphere, had in fact forged economic weapons of unparalleled strength for use in the interests of national policy. A German staff officer had remarked to Engels in the 1880s that ‘the basis of warfare is primarily the general economic life of peoples’;26 and this diagnosis was amply confirmed by the experiences of 1914–18. In no previous war had the economic life of belligerent nations been so completely and ruthlessly organized by the political authority. In the age-long alliance between the military and the economic arm, the economic arm for the first time was an equal, if not a superior, partner. To cripple the economic system of an enemy Power was as much a war aim as to defeat his armies and fleets. ‘Planned economy’, which means the control by the state for political purposes of the economic life of the nation, was a development of the first world war.27 ‘War potential’ has become another name for economic power.

We have now therefore returned, after the important, but abnormal, laissez-faire interlude of the nineteenth century, to the position where economics can be frankly recognized as a part of politics. We can thus resolve the controversy, which is in large part a product of nineteenth-century ideas and terminology, about the so-called economic interpretation of history. Marx was overwhelmingly right when he insisted on the increasing importance of the role played by economic forces in politics; and since Marx, history can never be written again exactly as it was written before him. But Marx believed, just as firmly as did the laissez-faire liberal, in an economic system with laws of its own working independently of the state, which was its adjunct and its instrument. In writing as if economics and politics were separate domains, one subordinate to the other, Marx was dominated by nineteenth-century presuppositions in much the same way as his more recent opponents who are equally sure that ‘the primary laws of history are political laws, economic laws are secondary’.28 Economic forces are in fact political forces. Economics can be treated neither as a minor accessory of history, nor as an independent science in the light of which history can be interpreted. Much confusion would be saved by a general return to the term ‘political economy’, which was given the new science by Adam Smith himself and not abandoned in favour of the abstract ‘economics’, even in Great Britain itself, till the closing years of the nineteenth century.29 The science of economics presupposes a given political order, and cannot be profitably studied in isolation from politics.

Some fallacies of the separation of economics from politics

It would have been unnecessary to dwell at length on this point if its importance had been either purely historical or purely theoretical. The illusion of a separation between politics and economics – a belated legacy of the laissez-faire nineteenth century – had ceased to correspond to any aspect of current reality. But it continued to persist in thought about international politics, where it created no little confusion. An immense amount of discussion was devoted to the meaningless question whether (as the Economic Conference of 1927 supposed)30 our political troubles have economic causes or whether (as the Van Zeeland report suggested)31 our economic troubles have political causes, and to the equally meaningless conundrum whether the problem of raw materials is political or economic. Similar confusion was produced by the declaration of the British Government in 1922 that the rate of Jewish immigration into Palestine would be determined by ‘the economic capacity of the country’, supplemented in I93I by the further statement that ‘the considerations relevant to the limits of absorptive capacity are purely economic considerations’. It was not until 1937 that a Royal Commission discovered that ‘since Arabs are hostile to Jewish immigration, the factor of “hostility between the two peoples” necessarily assumes immediate economic importance’.32 Indeed every issue of migration and refugees has been complicated by the supposition that there is some objective economic test of absorptive capacity. The conflict between two opposite and equally defensible interpretations of the promise in the Treaty of Neuilly ‘to ensure the economic outlets of Bulgaria to the Aegean Sea’ was another instance of confusion arising from the too light-hearted use of this elusive word. Attempts to solve international problems by the application of economic principles divorced from politics are doomed to sterility.

The most conspicuous practical failure caused by the persistence of this nineteenth-century illusion was the breakdown of League sanctions in 1936. Careful reading of the text of Article 16 of the Covenant acquits its framers of responsibility for the mistake. Paragraph 1 prescribes the economic weapons, paragraph 2 the military weapons, to be employed against the violator of the Covenant. Paragraph 2 is clearly complementary to paragraph 1, and assumes as a matter of course that, in the event of an application of sanctions, ‘armed forces’ would be required ‘to protect the Covenants of the League’. The only difference between the two paragraphs is that, whereas all members of the League would have to apply the economic weapons, it would be natural to draw the necessary armed forces from those members which possessed them in sufficient strength and in reasonable geographical proximity to the offender.33 Subsequent commentators, obsessed with the assumption that economics and politics were separate and separable things, evolved the doctrine that paragraphs 1 and 2 of Article 16 were not complementary, but alternative, the difference being that ‘economic sanctions’ were obligatory and ‘military sanctions’ optional. This doctrine was eagerly seized on by the many who felt that the League might conceivably be worth a few million pounds’ worth of trade, but not a few million human lives; and in the famous 1934 Peace Ballot in Great Britain, some two million deluded voters expressed simultaneously their approval of economic, and their disapproval of military, sanctions. ‘One of the many conclusions to which I have been drawn’, said Lord Baldwin at this time, ‘is that there is no such thing as a sanction which will work, which does not mean war.’34 But the bitter lesson of 1935–36 was needed to drive home the truth that in sanctions, as in war, the only motto is ‘all or nothing’, and that economic power is impotent if the military weapon is not held in readiness to support it.35 Power is indivisible; and the military and economic weapons are merely different instruments of power.36

A different, and equally serious, form in which this illusory separation of politics and economics can be traced is the popular phraseology which distinguishes between ‘power’ and ‘welfare’, between ‘guns’ and ‘butter’. ‘Welfare arguments are “economic”,’ remarks an American writer, ‘power arguments are “political”.’37 This fallacy is particularly difficult to expose because it appears to be deducible from a familiar fact. Every modern government and every parliament is continually faced with the dilemma of spending money on armaments or social services; and this encourages the illusion that the choice really lies between ‘power’ and ‘welfare’, between political guns and economic butter. Reflexion shows, however, that this is not the case. The question asked never takes the form, Do you prefer guns or butter? For everyone (except a handful of pacifists in those Anglo-Saxon countries which have inherited a long tradition of uncontested security) agrees that, in case of need, guns must come before butter. The question asked is always either, Have we already sufficient guns to enable us to afford some butter? or, Granted that we need x guns, can we increase revenue sufficiently to afford more butter as well? But the neatest exposure of this fallacy comes from the pen of Professor Zimmern; and the exposure is none the less effective for being unconscious. Having divided existing states on popular lines into those which pursue ‘welfare’ and those which pursue ‘power’, Professor Zimmern revealingly adds that ‘the welfare states, taken together, enjoy a preponderance of power and resources over the power states’,38 thereby leading us infallibly to the correct conclusion that ‘welfare states’ are states which, already enjoying a preponderance of power, are not primarily concerned to increase it, and can therefore afford butter, and ‘power states’ those which, being inferior in power, are primarily concerned to increase it, and devote the major part of their resources to this end. In this popular terminology, ‘welfare states’ are those which possess preponderant power, and ‘power states’ those which do not. Nor is this classification as illogical as it may seem. Every Great Power takes the view that the minimum number of guns necessary to assert the degree of power which it considers requisite takes precedence over butter, and that it can only pursue ‘welfare’ when this minimum has been achieved. For many years prior to 1933, Great Britain, being satisfied with her power, was a ‘welfare state’. After 1935, feeling her power contested and inadequate, she became a ‘power state’; and even the Opposition ceased to press with any insistence the prior claim of the social services. The contrast is not one between ‘power’ and ‘welfare’, and still less between ‘politics’ and ‘economics’, but between different degrees of power. In the pursuit of power, military and economic instruments will both be used.

Autarky

Having thus established that economics must properly be regarded as an aspect of politics, we may divide into two broad categories the methods by which economic power is pressed into the service of national policy. The first will contain those measures whose purpose is defined by the convenient word autarky; the second, economic measures directly designed to strengthen the national influence over other countries.

Autarky, or self-sufficiency, was one of the aims of the mercantilist policy, and has indeed been pursued by states from the earliest times. But the problem of autarky is nevertheless distinctively modern. In the Middle Ages, autarky was a natural and necessary condition of economic life; for the long-distance transport of any goods other than those of small bulk and great value was unremunerative. From the close of the Middle Ages, transport gradually became safer, cheaper and more rapid. Countries became less completely self-dependent; and a rising standard of life was based in part on the international exchange of specialized products. But it is only within the last hundred years that the coming of steam has made transport by land and sea so rapid and cheap that the cost of transport of most commodities is now insignificant in relation to the cost of production, and it is in many cases immaterial whether an article is produced 500 or 5000 miles from the point where it will be used or consumed. Mass-production methods, under which commodities become cheaper the more of them are produced in the same place, have further promoted concentration. Not only are our needs today more highly specialized than ever before, but we live in a world where, for the first time in history, it might, from the standpoint of cost, be possible – and perhaps even desirable – to grow all the wheat consumed by the human race in Canada, and all the wool in Australia, to manufacture all the motor cars in Detroit and all the cotton clothing in England or Japan. Internationally, the consequences of absolute laissez-faire are as fantastic and as unacceptable as are the consequences of laissez-faire within the state. In modern conditions the artificial promotion of some degree of autarky is a necessary condition of orderly social existence.

Autarky is, however, not only a social necessity, but an instrument of political power. It is primarily a form of preparedness for war. In the mercantilist period, it was commonly asserted, both in Britain and elsewhere, that the military power of the state depended on the production of manufactured goods. Adam Smith made his famous exceptions to the doctrine of laissez-faire when he approved of the British Navigation Act and the bounties on British sail-cloth and British gunpowder. But the principle of autarky received its classic definition from the pen of Alexander Hamilton, who in 1791, being then Secretary of the United States Treasury, made a report to the House of Representatives which enunciates, in words which might have been written to-day, the whole modern doctrine of autarky. Hamilton had been instructed to advise on ‘the means of promoting such [manufactures] as will tend to render the United States independent of foreign nations for military and other essential supplies’. One short passage may be quoted from the report:

Not only the wealth but the independence and security of a country appear to be materially connected with the prosperity of manufactures. Every nation, with a view to these great objects, ought to endeavour to possess within itself all the essentials of national supply. . . . The extreme embarrassments of the United States during the late war, from an incapacity of supplying themselves, are still a matter of keen recollection; a future war might be expected to exemplify the mischief and dangers of a situation to which that capacity is still, in too great a degree, applicable, unless changed by timely and vigorous action.

And Hamilton went on to examine in turn all the methods by which the desired result might be attained – duties, prohibitions, bounties and premiums.39 In Germany, just fifty years later, List argued that ‘on the development of the German protective system depend the existence, the independence and the future of the German nationality’;40 and in the latter half of the nineteenth century successive Prussian victories drove home the intimate connexion between a highly developed industrial system and military power.

Throughout this period Great Britain, in virtue of her industrial supremacy, enjoyed virtually complete autarky in all industrial products, though not in the raw materials required to produce them. In food supplies, she ceased to be self-supporting about 1830. But this defect was in large part remedied by her naval power, the maintenance of which became one of her chief preoccupations. A Royal Commission on the Supply of Food and Raw Materials in Time of War, which reported in 1905, discussed, but rejected, plans for the precautionary storage in Great Britain of reserve supplies, and did not even discuss any plan for encouraging home production. Complete reliance was placed on the capacity of the navy to protect the ordinary channels of trade, and thereby make up for the inevitable absence of sufficient supplies at home.41 The now current view that nineteenth-century statesmen were not alive to the political desirability of autarky, or of some adequate substitute for it, is not borne out by facts.

The effect of the first world war on the whole concept of economics has already been discussed. The impulse which it gave to the pursuit of autarky was immediate and powerful. Blockade, and the diversion of a large part of the world’s shipping to the transport of troops and munitions, imposed more or less stringent measures of autarky on both belligerents and neutrals. For four years, the Central Powers were compelled to depend exclusively on their own resources, and to realize in spite of themselves Fichte’s ideal of The Closed Commercial State. Even for the Allied Powers, the new weapon of the submarine made reliance on overseas imports as an alternative to autarky more precarious than it had hitherto been supposed. Nor did the Allied Governments, at any rate, appear to regard autarky as a regrettable and temporary expedient. In June I9I6, they met in Paris to discuss postwar economic policy, and decided ‘to take the necessary steps without delay to render themselves independent of the enemy countries in so far as regards the raw materials and manufactured articles essential to their normal economic activities’.42 In the following year, a British Royal Commission drew up a list of articles in respect of which it had been established ‘that the possibility of economic pressure from foreign countries controlling supplies of raw materials requires especially to be guarded against, and that government action is most needed in order to promote economic independence’; and this policy was carried into effect in the Safeguarding of Industries Act of 1921. Where home supplies were not available, the unfettered control of overseas supplies became a primary objective. The desire to control adequate supplies of oil inspired an active British policy in more than one oil-producing country.

Internationally, the important part played by the blockade in winning the war made inevitable the prominence of ‘economic sanctions’ in the constitution of the League of Nations. It was clear that blockade was likely to be applied more vigorously than ever in another war; and autarky was developed as the natural defensive armament against the weapon of blockade. The actual use of this weapon against Italy in I93S added point to the moral. ‘November 18, 1935, marks the starting point of a new chapter in Italian history,’ said Mussolini to the National Guild Assembly on 23 March 1936. ‘. . . The new phase of Italian history will be determined by this postulate: to secure within the briefest time possible the greatest possible measure of economic independence.’ There was, in fact, little novelty in this doctrine, which was merely a paraphrase of what had been said by Hamilton, by List, and by the British Royal Commission of 1917. But the growing international tension threw the problem into sharp relief. A well-known American publicist urged the joint buying by Great Britain and the United States of ‘metals of strategic importance’ with the object of ‘removing the great bulk of these important metals from the markers in which the dictatorial and “have-not” Powers must buy them’.43 ‘No measure’, added a British writer, ‘would do more to weaken a German rearmament programme than a British decision to purchase the entire available output of Swedish ore.’44 It scarcely required such warnings to convince governments of the military value of autarky. The development of synthetic materials by Germany and the accumulation by Great Britain of stocks of foodstuffs and essential raw materials were two of many significant symptoms. Autarky, like other elements of power, is expensive. It may cost a country as much to make itself self-supporting in some important commodity as to build a battleship. The expenditure may turn out to be wasteful, and the acquisition not worth the cost. But to deny that autarky is an element of power, and as such desirable, is to obscure the issue.

Economic power as an instrument of policy

The second use of the economic weapon as an instrument of national policy, i.e. its use to acquire power and influence abroad, has been so fully recognized and freely discussed that the briefest summary will suffice here. It takes two principal forms: (a) the export of capital, and (b) the control of foreign markets.

(a) The export of capital has in recent times been a familiar practice of powerful states. The political supremacy of Great Britain throughout the nineteenth century was closely associated with London’s position as the financial centre of the world. Only in Europe, where Great Britain did not aspire to political influence, were British investments insignificant, amounting to not more than S per cent of all British capital invested abroad. The rise of the United States to political power in the present century was largely due to their appearance in the market as a large-scale lender, first of all, to Latin America, and since 1914, to Europe. The attainment of political objectives by direct government investment occurred in such cases as the purchase by the British Government of shares in the Suez Canal Company and the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, or the construction of the Chinese Eastern Railway with Russian Government capital. More often, governments used their power to stimulate investments by banks and private individuals in the interests of national policy. Thus the Franco-Russian alliance was cemented by some £400,000,000 of French capital lent by French investors to the Russian Government. In Germany, ‘the joint-stock bank was not merely a credit organization, but a politico-economic instrument; it was an instrument of Germany’s power policy’.45 The whole policy of nineteenth-century imperialism was based on the development of the backward parts of the world through investment of European capital. Political interests were furthered by private investors enjoying, like the chartered companies of the nineteenth century, government patronage or, more commonly, diplomatic support.46 Marx described the policy as one of replacing ‘the feudal method of waging war . . . by the mercantile method, cannon by capital’;47 and a new and expressive phrase was coined to describe the ‘dollar diplomacy’ of the United States.

The diplomacy of the present administration [said Taft in 1912] has sought to respond to the modern ideas of commercial intercourse. This policy has been characterised as substituting dollars for bullets. It is one that appeals alike to idealistic humanitarian sentiments, to the dictates of sound policy and strategy, and to legitimate commercial aims.48

The frequent appearances of the American fleet in Latin American waters (like those of the British fleet elsewhere) showed, moreover, that, if dollars were a humanitarian substitute for bullets, they could and would be reinforced by bullets in case of political need.

The diminished use after 1919 of capital investment abroad as an instrument of policy was explained by the rapid falling-off in the accumulation of surplus capital throughout the world and the insolvency of many potential borrowers. But numerous familiar examples may still be cited. France strengthened her influence over Poland and the Little Entente by abundant loans and credits, public and private, to these countries. Several governments granted or guaranteed loans to Austria for the political purpose of maintaining Austria’s independence; and in 1931 French financial pressure obliged Austria to abandon the project of a customs union between Austria and Germany. The rapid decline of French influence in Central Europe after 1931 was closely connected with the fact that France, since the crisis, was unable to continue her policy of financial assistance to these countries. When in December 1938 it was announced that the French Schneider-Creusot group had sold its interest in the Skoda works to a Czecho-Slovak group representing the Czecho-Slovak Government, a correspondent of The Times commented that ‘this transaction is another indication of France’s retreat from Central Europe, and puts an end to a chapter of French political expansion’.49 After 1932, when an unofficial embargo was placed on the issue of foreign loans in the British market, it could fairly be said that Great Britain’s foreign lending was subject to political supervision. The years 1938 and 1939 saw the grant to Turkey by Great Britain and Germany, and to China by the United States and Great Britain, of ‘commercial’ credits whose political motive was scarcely disguised.

(b) The struggle to control foreign markets provides a further illustration of the interaction of politics and economics; for it is often impossible to decide whether political power is being used to acquire markets for the sake of their economic value, or whether markets are being sought in order to establish and strengthen political power. The struggle for markets has been the most characteristic feature of the economic warfare of the period between the two world wars. It would be wrong to attribute exclusively to political rivalries the intensified pressure to export which manifested itself everywhere. Under the modern structure of industry, the most economical scale of production of many commodities exceeds the consumption capacity of most national markets; and to sell dear in a protected home market and cheap in a free foreign market (which is the essence of ‘dumping’) may be perfectly sound policy from the purely commercial standpoint. Yet the use of dumping as an instrument of policy is incontestable; and powerful countries found their ‘natural’ markets in areas where their political interests lay and where their political influence could be most readily asserted. The principal reason why Central and South-Eastern Europe were Germany’s ‘natural’ markets was their accessibility to Germany’s military power. German rearmament and German economic penetration of these areas proceeded simultaneously. This was, however, not a new phenomenon. An admirable example of the intertwining of political and economic power may be found in the British position in Egypt. British economic penetration in Egypt in the last two decades of the nineteenth century resulted from British military occupation, which was designed to protect British interests in the Suez Canal, which had been acquired to protect British trade routes and strategic lines of communication.

The methods used to encourage exports and capture foreign markets are too familiar to need discussion. The simplest of all is the granting of loans or credits to finance exports. Before 1914 Great Britain was so little preoccupied with the problem of markets that loans obtained in London by foreign borrowers were free of any condition as to where the proceeds should be spent. Foreign loans obtained elsewhere frequently carried the condition that the whole or part of the proceeds should be expended by the borrower in the lending country.50 Since 1919 this condition has been almost universally applied. In Great Britain, two governmental institutions – the Colonial Development Fund and the Export Credits Guarantee Department – were engaged in financing British exports, the first to the Empire, the second to foreign countries. Before 1939, the operations of the Export Credits Guarantee Department were officially described as being of a purely commercial character. But by an act passed in 1939, the limit of the guarantees which might be given by the Department was increased, and a sum of £10,000,000 was earmarked for the guaranteeing of transactions ‘in connection with which it appears to them [i.e. the Board of Trade] expedient in the national interest that guarantees should be given’.51 In introducing this measure into the House of Commons, the President of the Board of Trade denied the suggestion that Great Britain ‘had declared a trade war upon Germany’, but described the measure as one of ‘economic rearmament’ and added that ‘the economic rearmament which we are trying now to undertake is exactly like our other rearmament’.52 In July 1939, the amount of £I0,000,000 was increased to £60,000,000. Export bounties and currency manipulation are merely indirect forms of export credits.

The most characteristic modern method of acquiring markets and the political power which goes with them is, however, the reciprocal trade agreement – the return to a system of thinly disguised barter. Thus British purchases of meat and cereals in the Argentine and of bacon and butter in Denmark and the Baltic States secured markets in those countries for British coal and British manufactures. The Ottawa Agreements were a slightly more complicated variation on the same theme. In the Central European and Balkan countries Germany, by purchasing local products (mainly cereals and tobacco) for which no other lucrative outlet could be found, secured not only a market for German goods, but a sphere of political influence. One of the symptoms of the artificial character of French political influence in this region was failure to secure any substantial share in its trade. Purchasing power had become an international asset; and the fact that price was no longer the dominant factor (Germany made most of her purchases in South-Eastern Europe at rates above world prices) put the purchaser and not the producer in a position to call the tune. A new power has thus been placed in the hands of countries with a large population and a high standard of living. But it is a wasting asset which, if used to excess, tends to destroy itself.

Economic power and international morality

One concluding reflexion may round off this summary sketch of the use of the economic weapon as an instrument of political power. The substitution of the economic weapon for the military weapon – what Marx calls the replacement of cannon by capital – is a symptom not so much of superior morality as of superior strength. This can be seen from a few simple examples. Great Britain, aggrieved by the trial of the Metro-Vickers engineers in Moscow, could obtain satisfaction by imposing an embargo on Soviet imports. Italy, aggrieved by the murder of an Italian officer, could not avail herself of this economic expedient (for an Italian embargo on Greek imports would have been negligible); she could obtain satisfaction only by the brutal military method of bombarding Corfu. In 1931, Great Britain established what came to be known as a ‘sterling bloc’ by methods which were non-political and in appearance largely fortuitous. Germany, in order to establish an equivalent ‘mark bloc’ in Central and South-Eastern Europe, had to resort to methods which were frankly political and included the use and threatened use of force. British economic and financial strength enabled Great Britain to refrain from intervention in the Spanish civil war. The British Government relied on ‘sterling bullets’ to prevent the permanent predominance of Germany and Italy in Spain, whatever the issue of the war. As regards the Far East, the Prime Minister in the same period remarked that ‘when the war is over, and the reconstruction of China begins, she cannot possibly be reconstructed without some help from this country’.53 The growing strength of the United States in international trade and finance was one, at any rate, of the reasons which allowed the United States Government to abandon its traditional practice of landing marines in the territory of recalcitrant Latin American republics and to adopt the ‘good neighbour’ policy.

The point, however, has a wider application to the whole problem of ‘aggression’ and territorial annexation. One of the most revealing documents on this aspect of power is a despatch from the Russian Chargé d’Affaires in Peking to the Russian Government in 1910:

Should we be sufficiently powerful economically [wrote this frank diplomat], it would be simpler to direct all our efforts to the conclusion of an economic treaty. If, however, as I fear, we should by so doing only be of service to foreigners and ourselves be unable to secure any profits from what had been achieved (thus we have for instance in reality been unable to profit by the extraordinary advantages embodied in the commercial treaty of 1881), then there is, in my opinion, no reason to depart from the basis of policy we have followed hitherto, that of territorial acquisition.54

A recent British writer on the Far East has made a similar observation:

Free Trade, as championed by England in the nineteenth century, was the cause of the stronger in purely commercial competition. The ‘sphere of influence’ with its special rights was the objective of states which sought to compensate for weakness in such competition by the direct application of political power.55

Great Britain’s unchallenged naval and economic supremacy throughout the nineteenth century enabled her to establish a commanding position in China with a minimum of military force and of economic discrimination. A relatively weak Power like Russia could only hope to achieve a comparable result by naked aggression and annexation. Japan afterwards learned the same lesson. In his well-known memorandum of January 1907, Crowe argued that Great Britain was ‘the natural protector of the weaker communities’, and that by her free-trade policy of an open market ‘she undoubtedly strengthens her hold on the interested friendship of other nations’.56 The argument might have been developed by adding that Great Britain, in virtue of her inherent economic strength and the free-trade policy made possible by it, was able to exercise in many countries a measure of indirect influence and control which no other Power could have achieved without interference with the political independence of the countries concerned, and that this advantage made it as natural for Great Britain, as it would have been difficult for others, to appear as a champion of the political independence of small nations. In Egypt, Great Britain has reconciled her military and economic predominance with the formal independence of the country, where a weaker Power would have had to resort to annexation to obtain a similar effect. Great Britain was able to abandon her formal authority over Iraq and to maintain her interests there, while France shrank from the same step in Syria. The economic weapon is pre-eminently the weapon of strong Powers. It is significant that a proposal made by the Soviet Government in 1931 for a pact of ‘economic non-aggression’ was received with the greatest hostility by the three most powerful countries of the day: Great Britain, France and the United States.

Nevertheless, it is perhaps difficult to dismiss as unfounded the common view that the use of the economic weapon is less immoral than the use of the military weapon. This may not always be true. Blockade in time of war may cause as much suffering as a series of air raids. But generally speaking, there is a sense in which dollars are more humane than bullets even if the end pursued be the same. It is less immoral to place an embargo on Soviet imports than to bombard Greeks. It cannot be reasonably doubted that a form of economic control (such as that of the United States in Central America) which preserves a measure of political independence is more acceptable to subordinate nations, and therefore less immoral, than direct political control (such as that established by Germany in I939 in Bohemia and Moravia). The distinction is not entirely removed by pointing out that the United States, if she were economically as weak as Germany, might well have taken the same course. It is true that the poor are more likely to steal than the rich, and that this affects our moral judgment of individual cases of theft. But theft is generally recognized as per se immoral. This is merely an illustration of the way in which morality itself is involved in questions of power.

The moral issue will require consideration later. For the present, the most important lesson to be drawn in this field is the illusory character of the popular distinction between economic and military power. Power, which is an element of all political action, is one and indivisible. It uses military and economic weapons for the same ends. The strong will tend to prefer the minor and more ‘civilized’ weapon, because it will generally suffice to achieve his purposes; and as long as it will suffice, he is under no temptation to resort to the more hazardous military weapon. But economic power cannot be isolated from military power, nor military from economic. They are both integral parts of political power; and in the long run one is helpless without the other.

(c) Power over opinion

Power over opinion is the third form of power. The ‘Jingoes’ who sang ‘We’ve got the ships, we’ve got the men, we’ve got the money too’ had accurately diagnosed the three essential elements of political power: armaments, manpower and economic power. But manpower is not reckoned by mere counting of heads. ‘The Soldan of Egypt or the Emperor of Rome’, as Hume remarked, ‘might drive his harmless subjects like brute beasts against their sentiments and inclinations. But he must at least have led his mamelukes or pretorian bands like men by their opinions.’57 Power over opinion is therefore not less essential for political purposes than military and economic power, and has always been closely associated with them. The art of persuasion has always been a necessary part of the equipment of political leader. Rhetoric has a long and honoured record in the annals of statesmanship. But the popular view which regards propaganda as a distinctively modern weapon is, none the less, substantially correct.

Propaganda in the modern world

The most obvious reason for the increasing prominence attached to power over opinion in recent times is the broadening of the basis of politics, which has vastly increased the number of those whose opinion is politically important. Until comparatively modern times, those whose opinion it was worth while to influence were few in number, united by close ties of interest and, generally speaking, highly educated; and the means of persuasion were correspondingly limited. ‘Scientific exposition’, in Hitler’s words, is for the intelligentsia. The modern weapon of propaganda is for the masses.58 Christianity seems to have been the first great movement in history with a mass appeal. Appropriately enough, it was the Catholic church which first understood and developed the potentialities of power over large masses of opinion. The Catholic church in the Middle Ages was – and has, within the limits of its power, remained – an institution for diffusing certain opinions and extirpating other opinions contrary to them: it created the first censorship and the first propaganda organization. There is much point in the remark of a recent historian that the mediaeval church was the first totalitarian state.59 The Reformation was a movement which simultaneously deprived it, in several parts of Europe, of its power over opinion, of its wealth and of the authority which the military power of the Empire had conferred on it.

The problem of power over opinion in its modern mass form has been created by developments in economic and military technique – by the substitution of mass-production industries for individual craftsmanship and of the conscript citizen army for the volunteer professional force. Contemporary politics are vitally dependent on the opinion of large masses of more or less politically conscious people, of whom the most vocal, the most influential and the most accessible to propaganda are those who live in and around great cities. The problem is one which no modern government ignores. In appearance, the attitude adopted towards it by democracies and by totalitarian states is diametrically opposed. Democracies purport to follow mass opinion; totalitarian states set a standard and enforce conformity to it. In practice, the contrast is less clear cut. Totalitarian states, in determining their policy, profess to express the will of the masses; and the profession is not wholly vain. Democracies, or the groups which control them, are not altogether innocent of the arts of moulding and directing mass opinion. Totalitarian propagandists, whether Marxist or Fascist, continually insist on the illusory character of the freedom of opinion enjoyed in democratic countries. There remains a solid substratum of difference between the attitude of democracies and totalitarian states towards mass opinion, which may prove a decisive factor in times of crisis. But both agree in recognizing its paramount importance.

The same economic and social conditions which have made mass opinion supremely important in politics have also created instruments of unparalleled range and efficiency for moulding and directing it. The oldest, and still perhaps the most powerful, of these instruments is universal popular education. The state which provides the education necessarily determines its content. No state will allow its future citizens to imbibe in its schools teaching subversive of the principles on which it is based. In democracies, the child is taught to prize the liberties of democracy; in totalitarian states, to admire the strength and discipline of totalitarianism. In both, he is taught to respect the traditions and creeds and institutions of his own country, and to think it better than any other. The influence of this early unconscious moulding is difficult to exaggerate. Marx’s dictum that ‘the worker has no country’ has ceased to be true since the worker has passed through national schools.

But when we speak of propaganda to-day, we think mainly of those other instruments whose use popular education has made possible: the radio, the film and the popular press. The radio, the film and the press share to the fullest extent the characteristic attribute of modern industry, i.e. that mass-production, quasi-monopoly and standardization are a condition of economical and efficient working. Their management has, in the natural course of development, become concentrated in fewer and fewer hands; and this concentration facilitates and makes inevitable the centralized control of opinion. The mass-production of opinion is the corollary of the mass-production of goods. Just as the nineteenth-century conception of political freedom was rendered illusory for large masses of the population by the growth and concentration of economic power, so the nineteenth-century conception of freedom of thought is being fundamentally modified by the development of these new and extremely powerful instruments of power over opinion. The prejudice which the word propaganda still excites in many minds to-day60 is closely parallel to the prejudice against state control of industry and trade. Opinion, like trade and industry, should according to the old liberal conception be allowed to flow in its own natural channels without artificial regulation. This conception has broken down on the hard fact that in modern conditions opinion, like trade, is not and cannot be exempt from artificial controls. The issue is no longer whether men shall be politically free to express their opinions, but whether freedom of opinion has, for large masses of people, any meaning but subjection to the influence of innumerable forms of propaganda directed by vested interests of one kind or another. In the totalitarian countries, radio, press and film are state industries absolutely controlled by governments. In democratic countries, conditions vary, but are everywhere tending in the direction of centralized control. Immense corporations are called into existence, which are too powerful and too vital to the community to remain wholly independent of the machine of government, and which themselves find it convenient to accept voluntary collaboration with the state as an alternative to formal control by it. The nationalization of opinion has proceeded everywhere pari passu with the nationalization of industry.

Propaganda as an instrument of policy

The organized use of power over opinion as a regular instrument of foreign policy is a modern development. Before 1914, cases occurred of the use of propaganda by governments in international relations. The press was freely used by Bismarck and other statesmen, though rather for the purpose of making pronouncements to foreign governments than as a means of influencing public opinion at large. Co-operation between the missionary and the trader, and the support of both by military force, was a familiar nineteenth-century example of unofficial association between propaganda and economic and military power in the interests of national expansion. But the field of propaganda was limited; and the only people who exploited it at all intensively were the revolutionaries. Any systematic resort to propaganda by governments would have been thought undignified and rather disreputable.

It did not take long for the belligerents of 1914-I8 to realize that ‘psychological war must accompany economic war and military war’.61 It was a condition of success on the military and economic fronts that the ‘morale’ of one’s own side should be maintained, and that of the other side sapped and destroyed. Propaganda was the instrument by which both these ends were pursued. Leaflets were dropped over the enemy lines inciting his troops to mutiny; and this procedure, like most new weapons of war, was at first denounced as being contrary to international law.62 Moreover, the new conditions of warfare nullified, in this as in so many other respects, the distinction between combatant and civilian; and the morale of the civilian population became for the first time a military objective.

Long-distance bombing [wrote the British Chief of Staff in January 1918] will produce its maximum moral effect only if visits are constantly repeated at short intervals so as to produce in each area bombed a sustained anxiety. It is this recurrent, as opposed to isolated spasmodic attacks, which interrupts industrial production and undermines public confidence.63

The military chiefs of other belligerent countries were doubtless considering the same problem in similar terms. The demoralization of the civilian population was the primary objective not only of many air raids but of the German long-range bombardment of Paris by ‘big Bertha’; and the work of the bomb and the shell was reinforced, especially during the last months of the war, by an intense output of printed propaganda. Throughout the first world war the close interdependence between the three forms of power was constantly demonstrated. The success of propaganda on both sides, both at home and in neutral and enemy countries, rose and fell with the varying fortunes of the military and economic struggle. When at length the Allied blockade and Allied victories in the field crippled German resources, Allied propaganda became enormously effective and played a considerable part in the final collapse. The victory of 1918 was achieved by a skilful combination of military power, economic power and power over opinion.

Notwithstanding the general recognition of the importance of propaganda in the later stages of the war, it was still regarded by almost everyone as a weapon specifically appropriate to a period of hostilities. ‘In the same way as I send shells into the enemy trenches, or as I discharge poison gas at him,’ wrote the German general who was primarily responsible for despatching Lenin and his party in the sealed train to Russia, ‘I, as an enemy, have the right to use propaganda against him.’64 The abolition of ministries and departments of propaganda at the end of the war was an automatic measure of demobilization. Yet within twenty years of the armistice, in what was still formally a time of peace, many governments were conducting propaganda with an intensity unsurpassed in the war period; and new official or semi-official agencies for the influencing of opinion at home and abroad were springing up in every country. This new development was rendered possible and inevitable by the popularization of international politics and by the growing efficiency of propaganda methods. Since both these processes are likely to continue, its permanence seems assured.

The initiative in introducing propaganda as a regular instrument of international relations must be credited to the Soviet Government. The causes of this were partly accidental. The Bolsheviks, when they seized power in Russia, found themselves desperately weak in the ordinary military and economic weapons of international conflict. The principal element of strength in their position was their influence over opinion in other countries; and it was therefore natural and necessary that they should exploit this weapon to the utmost. In early days, they seriously believed in their ability to dissolve the German armies by the distribution of propaganda leaflets and by fraternization between the lines. Later, they counted on propaganda in Allied countries to paralyse Allied intervention against them in the civil war. Had not propaganda been supplemented by the creation of an effective Red Army, it might by itself have proved ineffective. But the importance of the role it played is sufficiently indicated by the fear of Bolshevik propaganda felt for many years afterwards, and not yet extinct in many European and Asiatic countries. Soviet Russia was the first modern state to establish, in the form of the Communist International, a large-scale permanent international propaganda organization.

There was, however, a profounder cause why control over opinion should have taken a foremost place in the policy of Soviet Russia. Since the end of the Middle Ages, no political organization had claimed to be the repository of universal truth or the missionary of a universal gospel. Soviet Russia was the first national unit to preach an international doctrine and to maintain an effective world-propaganda organization. So revolutionary did this innovation appear that the Communist International purported at the outset to be wholly unconnected with the power of the Soviet Government. But this separation, which may have been effective in details of administration, never extended to major issues of policy; and after the Soviet state had been consolidated under Stalin, the separation became no more than a polite fiction. This development had far more than a local significance, and gives us the clue to the whole problem of the place of what are now known as ‘ideologies’ in international politics. For if it be true that power over opinion cannot be dissociated from other forms of power, then it appears to follow that, if power cannot be internationalized, there can be no such thing in politics as international opinion, and international propaganda is as much a contradiction in terms as an international army. This view, paradoxical as it may appear, can be supported by extremely cogent arguments; and both it and its implications require careful examination.

National or international propaganda?

Most political ideas which have strongly influenced mankind have been based on professedly universal principles and have therefore had, at any rate in theory, an international character. The ideas of the French Revolution, free trade, communism in its original form of 1848 or in its reincarnation of 1917, Zionism, the idea of the League of Nations, are all at first sight (as they were in intention) examples of international opinion divorced from power and fostered by international propaganda. But reflexion will set limits on this first impression. How far were any of these ideas politically effective until they took on a national colour and were supported by national power? The answer is not easy. Albert Sorel has a well-known passage on the course taken by the enthusiasm of the French revolutionaries:

They confuse . . . the propagation of the new doctrines with the extension of French power, the emancipation of mankind with the greatness of the Republic, the rule of reason with that of France, the liberation of peoples with the conquest of states, the European revolution with the domination of the French Revolution over Europe.65

The military power of Napoleon was notoriously the most potent factor in the propagation throughout Europe of the ideas of 1789. The political influence of the idea of free trade dated from its adoption by Great Britain as the basis of British policy. The revolutionaries of 1848 failed everywhere to achieve political power; and the ideas of 1848 remained barren. Neither the First nor the Second International attained any real authority. As 1914 showed, there were national labour movements, but there was no international labour movement. The Third or Communist International enjoyed little influence until the power of the Russian state was placed behind it; and Stalin has garbled and disseminated the ideas of 1917 in much the same way as Napoleon garbled and disseminated the ideas of 1789. Trotskyism, unsupported by the power of any state, remains without influence. Zionism, politically impotent so long as it relied solely on international propaganda, is effective in so far as it can count on the political backing of Great Powers. Propaganda is ineffective as a political force until it acquires a national home and becomes linked with military and economic power.

The fate of the League of Nations and of propaganda on its behalf is perhaps the best modern illustration of this tendency. As has been shown, men like Woodrow Wilson and Lord Cecil conceived the League of Nations as an expression of ‘the organized opinion of mankind’ controlling the military and economic power of governments. International public opinion was the supreme instrument of power (’by far the strongest weapon we have’); and this opinion was to be created by international propaganda which took no heed of frontiers.* Throughout the nineteen-twenties, this fallacy of the power of international opinion was being gradually exposed. That it survived at all was due to the persistent use by League enthusiasts of slogans like peace and disarmament which were capable of a universal appeal precisely because they meant different, and indeed contradictory, things to different people. Every country wanted to achieve the aims of its policy without war, and therefore stood for peace. Every country wanted disarmament of other countries or disarmament in those weapons which it did not regard as vital to itself. After the collapse of the Disarmament Conference, it became apparent to all that the League of Nations could be effective only in so far as it was an instrument of the national policy of its most powerful members. Opinion in favour of the League ceased altogether to be international, and was confined to those countries where the League was felt to be serving ends of national policy. In Great Britain the League of Nations became for the first time popular with what might be called the nationalist wing of the Conservative Party.

The fallacy of belief in the efficacy of an international public opinion divorced from national power may be further illustrated by developments elsewhere. The group of movements conveniently classified under the rubric of Fascism was based on certain professedly universal principles such as the rejection of democracy and class warfare, the insistence on leadership, and so forth. In its early days, Fascism was authoritatively described as ‘not an article for export’, and was for many years so treated by the countries which adhered to it. At a later date this limitation was explicitly disclaimed,66 and Fascism became the theme of a vigorous international propaganda in many parts of the world. It would, however, be a superficial diagnosis to pretend that, while the League of Nations and the Communist International began as instruments of international opinion and ended as instruments of national policy, Fascism began as an instrument of national policy and ended as an instrument of international opinion. In both cases, the international phase was an illusion (which does not mean that many people may not sincerely believe in it). International propaganda for Fascism was an instrument of the national policy of certain states, and grew with the growth of the military and economic power of those states. But the reductio ad absurdum of international ideological propaganda as a cloak for national policy came with the adoption of negative slogans designed to unite in a political alliance those who shared no positive ideology in common. Thus the Anti-Comintern Pact did not prevent Germany from coming to an agreement with the principal Communist Power when the needs of national policy seemed to require it; and the ‘anti-Fascism’ of the democratic nations did not deter them from seeking the alliance of countries whose forms of government were indistinguishable from Fascism. These slogans had no meaning or substance apart from the national policies of the countries by which they were used. Power over opinion cannot be dissociated from military and economic power.

International agreements regarding propaganda

Propaganda is now so well recognized as a national political weapon that stipulations regarding its use are fairly common in international agreements. Such stipulations were, appropriately enough, first introduced into agreements made with the Soviet Government for the purpose of limiting the activities of the Communist International. But this could still be thought of as an exceptional case. Outside Soviet Russia, the first recorded agreement to abstain from hostile propaganda seems to have been one concluded between the German and Polish Broadcasting Companies, which undertook to assure that ‘the matter broadcast does not in any way offend the national sentiment of listeners who are nationals of the other contracting party’.67 Propaganda was first raised to the dignity of a universal issue when the Polish Government made proposals to the Disarmament Conference for a convention on ‘moral disarmament’. To limit the propaganda weapon by a general convention proved as hopeless a task as to limit the military weapon.68 But bilateral agreements for terminating hostile propaganda were concluded between Germany and Poland in 1934 and between Germany and Austria in 1936;69 and in the Anglo-Italian Agreement of 16 April 1938, the two countries ‘placed on record their agreement that any attempt by either of them to employ the methods of publicity and propaganda at its disposal in order to injure the interests of the other would be inconsistent with the good relations which it is the object of the present agreement to establish’.

Such agreements create an obvious difficulty for democracies, which purport not to limit the free expression and publication of opinions about international affairs, and cannot therefore formally undertake to prevent propaganda on their territory against any country; and this embarrassment is reflected in the contorted phraseology of the Anglo-Italian Agreement. The fact is, however, that in the sphere of opinion, as in the economic sphere, the nineteenth-century principles of laissez-faire no longer hold good, even for democracies. Just as democratic governments have been compelled to control and organize economic life in their territories in order to compete with totalitarian states, so they find themselves at a disadvantage in dealing with these states if they are not in a position to control and organize opinion. Recognition of this fact grew rapidly even in Great Britain. In questions affecting international relations, a discreet influence, amounting in times of crisis to direct though unofficial censorship, was exercised even before the outbreak of the second world war over broadcasting, films and press; and though the use of this influence was frequently criticized in particular cases, it became clear that some such measures of restraint would be applied in similar circumstances by whatever government happened to be in power.70 Simultaneously, there was a rapid extension of propaganda designed to familiarize foreign opinion with the British point of view. Since 1935, a body called the British Council has exercised the function of ‘making the life and thought of the British peoples more widely known abroad’. In 1938, the British Broadcasting Corporation began the regular broadcasting of news bulletins in various foreign languages. In June 1939, the Prime Minister announced the creation of a new Foreign Publicity Department of the Foreign Office, which served as a nucleus for the Ministry of Information set up immediately on the outbreak of war.

Truth and morality in propaganda

We have hitherto discussed power over opinion in precisely the same terms as military and economic power; and the close connexion between these different forms of power is so vital, and has been so much neglected in theoretical discussion, that this seems the most fruitful approach to the problem at the present time. Some people might indeed argue that this is the only correct approach. For in the first place, opinion is conditioned by status and interest; and secondly, as we have seen in a previous chapter, a ruling class or nation, or dominant group of nations, not only evolves opinions favourable to the maintenance of its privileged position, but can, in virtue of its military and economic superiority, easily impose these opinions on others. The victory of the democratic countries in I9I8 created an almost universal opinion that democracy was the best form of government. In the nineteen-thirties, opinion in many parts of the world on the merits of Fascism as a form of government may be said, without much exaggeration, to have varied pari passu with the military and economic power of Germany and Italy in relation to the other Great Powers. These propositions could be supported by innumerable examples. If they were absolutely true, then power over opinion would in fact be indistinguishable in character from military and economic power, and there would be nothing which, given sufficient power and technical skill, men could not be made to believe. That this is the case has indeed sometimes been suggested. ‘By clever, persistent propaganda’, said Hitler, ‘even heaven can be represented to a people as hell, and the most wretched life as paradise’;71 and American advertising specialists are alleged to hold that ‘only cost limits the delivery of public opinion in any direction on any topic’.72 But these are the pardonable exaggerations of expert practitioners. As we shall see, even Hitler did not really believe in the unlimited power of propaganda to manufacture opinion. Here as elsewhere, the extreme realist position becomes untenable. When we set power over opinion side by side with military and economic power, we have none the less to remember that we are dealing no longer with purely material factors, but with the thoughts and feelings of human beings.

Absolute power over opinion is limited in two ways. In the first place, it is limited by the necessity of some measure of conformity with fact. There are objective facts which are not totally irrelevant to the formation of opinion. Good advertising may persuade the public that a face cream made of inferior materials is the best. But the most expert advertiser could not sell a face cream made of vitriol. Hitler condemned the futility of German propaganda in the first world war which depicted the enemy as ridiculous and contemptible. The propaganda was unsuccessful simply because it was, as the German soldier in the trenches discovered, untrue. This danger that ‘truth will out’, especially in an age of competitive propaganda, is a serious limitation on power over opinion. Education, which is one of the strongest instruments of this power, tends at the same time to promote a spirit of independent enquiry which is also one of the strongest antidotes against it. In so far as it strains and interprets facts for a specific purpose, propaganda always contains within itself this potentially self-defeating element.

Secondly, power over opinion is limited – and perhaps even more effectively – by the inherent utopianism of human nature. Propaganda, harnessed to military and economic power, always tends to reach a point where it defeats its own end by inciting the mind to revolt against that power. It is a basic fact about human nature that human beings do in the long run reject the doctrine that might makes right. Oppression sometimes has the effect of strengthening the will, and sharpening the intelligence, of its victims, so that it is not universally or absolutely true that a privileged group can control opinion at the expense of the unprivileged. As Hitler himself wrote, ‘every persecution which lacks a spiritual basis’ has to reckon with a ‘feeling of opposition to the attempt to crush an idea by brute force’.73 And this vital fact gives us another clue to the truth that politics cannot be defined solely in terms of power. Power over opinion, which is a necessary part of all power, can never be absolute. International politics are always power politics; for it is impossible to eliminate power from them. But that is only part of the story. The fact that national propaganda everywhere so eagerly cloaks itself in ideologies of a professedly international character proves the existence of an international stock of common ideas, however limited and however weakly held, to which appeal can be made, and of a belief that these common ideas stand somehow in the scale of values above national interests. This stock of common ideas is what we mean by international morality.

Notes

*

|    |

See pp. 32–5.

1.

|    |

Lenin, Selected Works (Engl. transl.), vii. p. 295.

2.

|    |

Marx and Engels, Works (Russian ed.), vii. p. 212.

3.

|    |

Even Lord Baldwin committed himself in I92S to the dangerous half-truth that ‘democracy is government by discussion, by talk’ (On England, p. 95). In a recent letter to The Times, Mr Frederic Harrison remarks of the British Commonwealth of Nations that it ‘is not founded on conquest and held together by force of arms. It has been acquired not by the force of our navy and our army but by force of character, and knit together by ties of sympathy, of a common interest, a common language and a common history’ (The Times, 30 June 1938). This, too, is a dangerous half-truth, which burkes the other and equally important half of the truth, i.e. that the British Commonwealth is held together by the immense military and economic power of Great Britain and would at once dissolve if that power were lost.

4.

|    |

Report to the Sixteenth Congress of the Russian Communist Party reprinted in L’Union Soviétique et la Cause de la Paix, p. 25; The Times, 26 June 1939. The italics have been inserted in both cases.

5.

|    |

Intimate Papers of Colonel House, ed. C. Seymour, iv. p. 24.

6.

|    |

Miller, The Drafting of the Covenant, ii. p. 61. The result of the subsequent enlargements of the Council has already been mentioned (p. 40 note 12).

7.

|    |

The Foreign Policy of the Powers (1935: reprinted from Foreign Affairs), pp. 86–7.

8.

|    |

League of Nations: Sixteenth Assembly, Part II. p. 49.

9.

|    |

In 1926, when Palestine was discussed by the Mandates Commission, M. Rappard ‘thought that the Mandatory would incur grave responsibility if it found itself one day faced with the impossibility of preventing a pogrom owing to insufficient troops. Its responsibility, indeed, would be shared by the Mandates Commission, if that Commission had not pointed out this danger’ (Permanent Mandates Commission, Minutes of Ninth Session, p. 184). The responsibility of the Commission was thus limited to ‘pointing out’.

10.

|    |

Lugard, The Dual Mandate in Tropical Africa, p. 53.

11.

|    |

B. Russell, Power, p. 11. I owe to this book, which is an able and stimulating analysis of power as ‘the fundamental concept in social science’, the tripartite classification of power adopted above.

12.

|    |

Lenin, Collected Works (Engl. transl.), xviii. p. 97; Theses of the Sixth Congress of Comintern quoted in Taracouzio, The Soviet Union and International Law, p. 436.

13.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 749.

14.

|    |

R. G. Hawtrey, Economic Aspects of Sovereignty, p. 107.

15.

|    |

It is perhaps necessary to recall the part played in British politics in 1914 by the threat of the Conservative Party to support revolutionary action in Ulster.

16.

|    |

R. G. Hawtrey, Economic Aspects of Sovereignty, p. 105.

17.

|    |

League of Nations: Official Journal, May 1924, p. 578.

18.

|    |

R. Niebuhr, Moral Man and Immoral Society, p. 42.

19.

|    |

Machiavelli, Discorsi, I. i. ch. v.

20.

|    |

Hobbes, Leviathan, ch. xi.

21.

|    |

British and Foreign State Papers, ed. Hertslet, xc. p. 811.

22.

|    |

The distinction between the two systems is implicit in Saint-Simon’s prediction that the ‘industrial régime’ will succeed the ‘military régime’, and ‘administration’ replace ‘government’, better known in the form given to it by Engels that the ‘administration of things’ will replace the ‘government of men’ (quotations in Halévy, Ère des Tyrannies, p. 224).

23.

|    |

Angell, The Great Illusion, ch. ii.

24.

|    |

B. Bosanquet, Social and International Ideals, pp. 234–5.

25.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 158.

26.

|    |

Engels, Anti-Dühring (Engl. transl.), p. I95.

27.

|    |

Planned economy has been developed not only by international frictions, but by social frictions within the state. It can therefore be logically regarded both as a nationalist policy (’economic nationalism’) and as a socialist policy. The second aspect was irrelevant to my present argument, and has therefore been passed over in the text. According to Bruck (Social and Economic History of Germany, p. 157), the term Planwirtschaft was invented in Germany during the first world war. But the phrase der staatliche Wirtschaftsplan occurs in a composite Grundriss der Sozialӧkonomik (i. 424), published at Tu bingen just before the war, in the general sense of ‘state economic policy’.

28.

|    |

Moeller van den Bruck, Germany’s Third Empire, p. 50. The idea is a commonplace of National Socialist and Fascist writers.

29.

|    |

In Germany, ‘political economy’ was at first translated Nationalӧkonomie, which was tentatively replaced in the present century by Sozialӧkonomie.

30.

|    |

‘Economic conflicts and divergence of economic interest are perhaps the most serious and most permanent of all the dangers which are likely to threaten the peace of the world’ (League of Nations: C.E.I. 44, p. 7).

31.

|    |

‘I have deliberately debarred myself from touching on the strictly political aspects. . . . It is, however, impossible to ignore the fact that we are working in their shadow’ (Report . . . on the Possibility of Obtaining a General Reduction of the Obstacles to International Trade, Cmd 5648).

32.

|    |

All these passages are quoted from the Report of the Palestine Royal Commission of 1937, Cmd 5479, pp. 298–300.

33.

|    |

This interpretation is confirmed by the report of the Phillimore Committee, on whose proposals the text of Article I6 was based. The Committee ‘considered financial and economic sanctions as being simply the contribution to the work of preventing aggression which might properly be made by countries which were not in a position to furnish actual military aid’ (International Sanctions: Report by a Group of Members of the Royal Institute of International Affairs, p. 115, where the relevant texts are examined).

34.

|    |

House of Commons, 18 May 1934; Official Report, col. 2139.

35.

|    |

It is not, of course, suggested that the military weapon must always be used. The British Grand Fleet was little used in the first world war. But it would be rash to assume that the result would have been much the same if the British Government had not been prepared to use it. What paralysed sanctions in 1935–36 was the common knowledge that the League Powers were not prepared to use the military weapon.

36.

|    |

It is worth noting that Stresemann was fully alive to this point when Germany entered the League of Nations. When the Secretary-General argued that Germany, if she contracted out of military sanctions, could still participate in economic sanctions, Stresemann replied: ‘We cannot do that either; if we take part in an economic boycott of a powerful neighbour, a declaration of war against Germany might be the consequence, since the exclusion of another country from intercourse with a nation of sixty million citizens would be a hostile act’ (Stresemann’s Diaries and Papers (Engl. transl.), ii. p. 69).

37.

|    |

F. L. Schuman, International Politics, p. 356.

38.

|    |

Zimmern, Quo Vadimus?, p. 41.

39.

|    |

Works of Alexander Hamilton, iv. pp. 69 sqq.

40.

|    |

List, The National System of Political Economy (Engl. transl.), p. 425.

41.

|    |

Supply of Food and Raw Materials in Time of War, Cmd 2644.

42.

|    |

The resolutions are printed in History of the Peace Conference, ed. Temperley, v. pp. 368–9.

43.

|    |

W. Y. Elliott in Political Quarterly, April–June 1938, p. 181.

44.

|    |

G. D. H. Cole in Political Quarterly, January–March 1939, p. 65.

45.

|    |

W. F. Bruck, Social and Economic History of Germany, p. 80.

46.

|    |

The whole subject is thoroughly investigated, and innumerable examples are cited, in Eugene Staley, War and the Private Investor. Mr Staley’s main conclusion is that official policy has rarely been influenced in an important degree by private investment, but that private investment has again and again been officially directed and encouraged as an instrument of policy.

47.

|    |

Marx, Gesammelte Schriften, i. p. 84.

48.

|    |

Annual Presidential Message to Congress, 3 December 1912.

49.

|    |

The Times, 29 December I938.

50.

|    |

Examples from France and Austria are quoted by C. K. Hobson, The Export of Capital (1914), p. I6. Russia and Belgium were also lending countries which commonly imposed this condition.

51.

|    |

It may be significant that in 1938 an official of the Foreign Office was transferred to the staff of the Export Credits Guarantee Department.

52.

|    |

House of Commons, 15 Dece5ber 1938: Official Report, col. 2319.

53.

|    |

House of Commons, 1 November I938, reprinted in N. Chamberlain, The Struggle for Peace, p. 340.

54.

|    |

B. de Siebert, Entente Diplomacy of the World War, p. 20.

55.

|    |

G. F. Hudson, The Far East in World Politics, p. 54.

56.

|    |

British Documents on the Origins of the War, ed. Gooch and Temperley, iii. p. 403.

57.

|    |

The Philosophical Works of David Hume, iv. p. 31.

58.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 196.

59.

|    |

G. G. Coulton, Mediaeval Panorama, p. 458 et al.

60.

|    |

‘I wish’, said the Home Secretary in the House of Commons on 28 July I939, ‘there had been no necessity for any Government publicity anywhere in the world. I still look forward to living long enough to see an end of this objectionable relic of the years of the war’ (Official Report, col. I834).

61.

|    |

H. D. Lasswell in the Foreword to G. G. Bruntz, Allied Propaganda and the Collapse of the German Empire. This book is the most comprehensive available account of its subject.

62.

|    |

In 1917, two British airmen captured by the Germans were sentenced to ten years’ hard labour for dropping such leaflets in contravention of the laws of war. The sentences were remitted on a British threat of reprisals. The practice was explicitly sanctioned in The Hague rules of 1923 for the conduct of aerial warfare (Bruntz, op. cit., pp. 142–4).

63.

|    |

The War in the Air (British Official History of the War), by H. A. Jones vi. Appendix VI, p. 26.

64.

|    |

Hoffmann, War Diaries (Engl. transl.), ii. p. 176.

65.

|    |

A Sorel, L’Europe et la Révolution Française, pp. 541–2.

66.

|    |

Mussolini, Scritti e Discorsi, vi. 151; vii. 230.

67.

|    |

League of Nations, C. 602, M. 240, 1931, ix, p. 4.

68.

|    |

An international convention under which the parties undertook to prevent the broadcasting from their territories of ‘incitements to war’, or in general hostile propaganda, against other contracting parties, was signed at Geneva by most of the surviving members of the League in September 1936 (League of Nations, C. 399 (I), M. 252 (I), 1936, xii).

69.

|    |

In both cases the agreement about propaganda did not figure in an officially published text, but its existence was disclosed in communiqués. The communiqué of the Austrian Foreign Office on the German-Austrian Agreement of 11 July I936, announced that ‘both countries are to refrain from all aggressive uses of the wireless, films, news services and the theatré (Documents on International Affairs, 1936, p. 324).

70.

|    |

A revealing debate on the press, initiated by the Liberal Opposition, took place in the House of Commons on 7 December 1938. While Liberal speakers argued for the freedom of the press on familiar nineteenth-century lines, the spokesman of the Labour Opposition declared that the freedom of the press was already illusory, and wanted to ‘make every newspaper in the country responsible for every item of news it prints and answerable to this House or some public authority’ (Official Report, col. 1293).

71.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 302.

72.

|    |

J. Truslow Adams, The Epic of America, p. 360.

73.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 187.